<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A refutation of a pamphlet, intituled in the English copy, A justification of the proceedings of the French-Church in London, about the suspension of Mr. Elijah Delmey</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58400</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833687</idno>
  <idno type="VID">38165</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240960617</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R752A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222524</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833687</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833687e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58400)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2176:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A refutation of a pamphlet, intituled in the English copy, A justification of the proceedings of the French-Church in London, about the suspension of Mr. Elijah Delmey</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>pPrinted by William Bentley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Stained and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Delmey, Elijah --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">French Protestant Church (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Justification of the proceedings of the French-Church in London, about the suspension of Mr. Elijah Delmey --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:1"/>
            <p>A REFUTATION OF A PAMPHLET, Intituled in the English COPY, A JUSTIFICATION of the Proceedings of the <hi>French-Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> about the Suspension of Mr. <hi>ELIJAH DELMEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Bentley.</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:3"/>
            <head>To the Christian READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE are very sensible, that the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Treatise to the world, will not advance the honour, or credit of the Strangers Churches in <hi>England:</hi> And therefore we have done it with much sorrow, and regret. But as the impulsive necessity of our Affairs requires, we cannot avoid it, (our sad, and unhappy differences having continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Church in <hi>London,</hi> almost two years.) And especially, since that the persons in Consistory of that Church, (when his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> the <hi>Lord PROTECTOR</hi> had graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously granted us a Colloquie of all our Churches,
<pb facs="tcp:38165:4"/> for the composing our differences, according to our Discipline, and Government,) did then print, and publish a Pamphlet in French, and English against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and faithfull Pastor,) and our selves, to defame us, as much as they could. An Action so strange! that the Parrallel was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver known, in any of the strangers Churches: And yet it was produced, and fomented chiefly by Mr. <hi>Christopher Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Baptista Stouppe,</hi> (two of the Pastors;) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom, we had good ground of complaint to our Colloquie, (as by the sequell will appear,) for being the grand disturbers of our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Peace. Wherefore at the meeting of some of our Deputies in Colloquie, in <hi>August,</hi> and <hi>September, 1656.</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> we complained against that <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> desiring it might be suppressed. But Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> presiding much with them, and those Deputies (being but five
<pb facs="tcp:38165:4"/> persons, and three of them not rightly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified) being inclined too much to partiality, (against the common Assent of sixe other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, also commissioned to sit in that Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, but some of them were, (against our Discipline) rejected,) we could have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresse. However, we have declined to refute that Pamplet, till this present, being four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Monthes since it's Edition: desiring ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Churches quiet, that all disputes might have acquiesced in silence, by a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Agreament amongst our selves. And therefore we proposed termes of Peace to our Consistory several times: And addressed the like by other Members of our Church: by an Elder also amongst them in Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; by Members of the <hi>Dutch Consistory;</hi> by Reverend <hi>English Divines:</hi> by W<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Citizens</hi> of <hi>London:</hi> And at length, af<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that both parties had submitted to the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:38165:5"/> and Judgement of several Reverend <hi>English Ministers</hi> before his <hi>Highness,</hi> (our Colloquie not rightly constituting, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly acting,) his <hi>Highness</hi> himself, (out of his eminent piety, and affection to settle us in Peace,) insisted much for an accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the Consistory designing to destroy all the Government of our Churches, and predominate by themselves, have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to utterly refused, all amicable Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures; and to make a <hi>Schisme,</hi> and Rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, have dispersed that <hi>Pamphlet</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> to Ministers, Souldiers, and others; and in <hi>Kent,</hi> and other parts of <hi>England;</hi> and also beyond the Seas. Wherefore, that too long forbearance of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swering that <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> may not be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an Argument against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> or our selves, of any Crime, or Offence, (as hath been conceived by some of our
<pb facs="tcp:38165:5"/> Friends, both in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Holland;)</hi> And being now so clearly, and absolutely ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified, and acquitted by so many severall Judicious, and Reverend persons in our proceedings, (as by this Treatise will be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,) We have therefore imprinted the same: Yet neverthelesse, we desired two of our Members to attend the Consistory: and Mr. <hi>John Jurin,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Peter du Ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> went accordingly; and before hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quested from them satisfaction, to be rendred to Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and our selves, (the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families,) for the injurie done us by that <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> But they refused to give any; standing upon their Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Courteous Reader,</hi> we intreat you to consider, how lamentable, and deplorable our condition is; that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> (with some of our Consistory,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:38165:6"/> the onely parties Delinquent, should neverthelesse be animated, and cherished by some persons publickly, and privately, to alter, and change our Discipline, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement; which (as it was,) could not have been more undermined, and opposed in the worst of times, by the very Bishops themselves: And yet through the blessing of God upon the purity, and zeal of our Ancestours, (from whom our Consistory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily degenerate,) our discipline, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (maugre all Malignities,) flourished in much honour, and esteem. But we seriously account it, to be the just hand of God upon us, for permitting such Ministers in our Church, who are scandalous, erroneous in their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, contentious, and Enemies to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Government of our Churches; Being justified, and asserted by some in Office of like qualifications. Wherefore from Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:38165:6"/> God, we wait for deliverance from our Oppressions, by the Power, and gracious aid of his <hi>Highness,</hi> and his <hi>Council;</hi> whose Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, and noble Favours, with all duty, and respect, we most gratefully recognize; And for our Churches reestablishment in tranquillity, and good Order, We most humbly implore his <hi>Highness,</hi> (after the glorious Examples of former Religious, and gracious Emperors,) to reflect some Raies of his power upon us; or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise our Lacerated, and mutilated Churches, and our Government will be totally Eclipsed.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38165:7"/>
            <head>A REFUTATION OF A PAMPHLET, Intituled in the English Copy, A Justification of the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>French-Church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> about the suspension of Mr. <hi>ELIJAH DELMEY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE plausible Title, and Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (by way of Insinuation,) of the said Pamphlet, (perhaps should they be pretermitted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Response,) might in comparing this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate therewith, obtein a Candid reception; As if the subject matters thereof were true:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38165:8"/> Whereas the Defendants (being a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Members of the said French-Church in London,) doubt not, but that to all indifferent, judicious, and impartial Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, their Defence, and Apology will be more acceptable, as being most true, conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and affirmative, both in Religion, and Reason.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Title,</hi> It may seem to some, as if it were the intire Act of the whole Church; Whereas in truth it is no other, than a clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Action of a part of the Consistory of the French-Church in London; and was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly disclamed by several Elders, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons thereof, as nugatory, and ludibrious; and also disapproved, and rejected by above 100, of the members of the Church in one day, upon the same Considerations.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Introduction, pag.</hi> 1, 2. (That each Paragraph may be dissected;) It is suggested, <hi>That the French Church in</hi> London, <hi>hath been troubled almost two yeers by Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>by renewing, and fomenting that unhappy Division, wherewith the Church had been vexed these many yeers: And therefore the Consistory (after several admonitions, and objurgations used to him, and his non-Conformity, and obduration in his Sin,) have suspended him from his Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38165:8"/> till he confess his faults, and return to his duty. Which action is pretended to be approved by all persons not prepossest, and to have satisfied many, offended at their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; although displeasing to Mr.</hi> Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey<hi>'s kindred, and other</hi> Factious persons; <hi>Who have presented to his</hi> Highnesse the Lord PROTECTOR, <hi>Petitions, full of impudent lies, and base calumnies against the Consistory; and dispersed</hi> Libels, <hi>and</hi> Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Papers <hi>among the</hi> English Ministers, <hi>rendring them odious to the Governours, both in Church, and State: They in the interim resting quiet upon the justice of their Cause; till truth should evince their Innocence, and frustrate their Enemies fraudulent practices: But finding their little care to justifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, hath made many to beleeve them guilty of the charges against them; they thought it imprudent, longer to abandon their cause, by a pernicious dissimulation, and shamefull silence: And thereupon they publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the causes of Mr.</hi> Delmey's <hi>suspension; that all might judge as well of his irregularity, and the injustice of his Abettors; as of the Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettors just actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto it is answered, That the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlettors have been very cautelous, or are (as they well may be,) ashamed to particularize
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38165:9"/> that renewed, and unhappy division by them mentioned: Nor can these Defendants col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect what they mean, or intend thereby; unless it be that Unchristian division, solely occasioned by Mr. <hi>Christopher Cisner</hi> in the time of Mr. <hi>De la Marche:</hi> When, some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, (now also abetting against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi>) did then unjustly confederate against Mr. <hi>De la Marche,</hi> (a Reverend Member of the late Assembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster,</hi>) and the Consistory, in such manner; That their riotous misbehaviours, being complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed against to the Magistrate, some of them were bound over to answer the Law for their offence, and to keep the publique peace: And Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> also was required to confesse his fault to Mr. <hi>De la Marche;</hi> which he did with tears; Embracing, and crying over him, <hi>(My Father, my Father.)</hi> Albeit he hath since hypocritically affirmed, that he did so mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of despight. And as for their unjust suspension of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (As in truth the Pamphletors themselves do not assert, that they have any warrant, or authority invested upon them by the Discipline, or any Acts of the Colloquies of the French-Churches in <hi>England,</hi> so to doe;) So the Defendants posi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirme, they have no power at all; nor can they so proceed, without convening some
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38165:9"/> other French Ministers, and Deputies of the Sister-Churches under the same Government in Colloquie, who are disinteressed in the dispute. For a single Consistory of it self, cannot suspend a Minister for any cause whatever: much more, after an Appeal made to a Colloquie: which in truth is Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey's</hi> Case, as the Pamphletors admit, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. And as of right, and in good Conscience they ought, so have the Generality of the members of the said Church (excepting one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part of the Consistory,) in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion publiquely dissented from the said unjust, and arbitrary proceedings against Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> (he being a godly Minister of the word of God, and blameless for his life, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the Congregation deprived of the edification of his Ministery, which they so much thirst after, and desire: Of whom, (though some are falsly, and uncharitably termed factious,) there are not above three persons, Fathers of families, related in kinred to Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> but many of them allyed to Mr. <hi>Cisner:</hi> And they that are so scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously traduced to be factious, are such Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the said Church, as have been Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers therein, (many of them,) longer than all those, or most of them, now in Consistory; and so were before Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> or Mr. <hi>John
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38165:10"/> Baptista Stouppe</hi> were Ministers thereof; and alwaies endeavoured to preserve the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Government of the Churches in unity, and peace.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Pamphlettors are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the Petitions to his Highnesse, as false, and opprobrious; The Defendants avouch the same as true; Which his Highnesse did not onely well approve of, (as may appear by his several gracious Answers, aswell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; as to the Pamphletors own Petition against them 12. <hi>Julii</hi> 1656;) But also the Reverend Divines, (to whom the Case was referred,) have judiciously, and impartially heard, and examined the truth thereof; and reported the same with their opinions to his Highnesse; as hereafter in this Treatise shall be manifested, where the inserting thereof will more naturally occurre.</p>
            <p>And so from the <hi>Introduction,</hi> we proceed to the Subjects of the Pamphletors preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded complaints against Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> as they are charged in nine heads, <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3, 4. For maintaining whereof the Pamphletors pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that they have convincing proofs: Some whereof they say, (and onely so,) that they will there produce, keeping others in reserve, if Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> have the Confidence to deny any thing charged against him. By
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38165:10"/> which, they would cunningly delude the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in captivating, and preoccupating, his judgement, from an expectation of some subsequent proofs to be contained in their Pamphlet, and which they further reserved; When as in truth they neither have therein, nor can they any waies hereafter make the least shadow of any thing, (they unjustly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi>) to appear by any honest, or conscientious Testimony in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and form, as they have stated their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: And for the Vindication of the credit, and innocency of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> We appeal to the persons mentioned by the Pamphlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, viz. Mr. <hi>Kerhuel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jurion,</hi> and Mr. <hi>De Fervacques;</hi> who are ready to justifie, and prove the contrary: And therefore being merely a libellous Defamation against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> it is not expedient to expend time in giving the said charges any particular An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers, or otherwise than in general, that they are untrue, and scandalous.</p>
            <p>And being in that Categorie, the future process against Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> by the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, hath not onely been without just ground, but also extrajudicial, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous; And albeit the Pamphletors suggest <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>their singular care to make orders to suppresse his disorders, and thereupon speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38165:11"/> the three Acts of the Consistory:</hi> Upon a general View, and Construction whereof, they may possibly seem to be very fair, and reasonable: yet if the ground, and original occasion of our unhappy differences be duly inquired into; it will be evident, that those Acts have been made out of a notorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to subvert, and destroy the Order, and Government of the said Church, setled, and established with so much Care, and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by our Predecessours; that brotherly love might be continued according to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian duty, without invading the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Consciences of any persons, or imposing upon them the Observation of any duty, not warranted by the word of God; And so to introduce, and erect a new forme of Government, to the hazard of the peace, and tranquillity of all the French-Churches in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore though the Pamphletors <hi>pag.</hi> 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliate to themselves a good Estimation by their gilded Arguments, and splendid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, for their preaching on daies, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Festivals,</hi>) as if they observed them, not for any sanctity, or solemnization, more than in common, and ordinary daies. Yet if the Christian Reader will be pleased
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38165:11"/> to consider the positive Acts of two Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies of all our Churches, rightly constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to our Discipline; one in the year 1644. and the other in 1654. <hi>absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prohibiting the observation of Holy daies, and publike exercises thereupon, in any manner whatsoever, (there being no prescript Rule for the same, either in the Doctrine of the Gospel, or of the Apostles;</hi>) he needs must hold us excused in conforming our selves to our Ecclesiastical Acts, in not observing such Festivities, introduced again into our Church in <hi>London</hi> onely, without the sentence, and Judgement of a Colloquie for the repealing thereof. And although the Institution, and celebration of such daies may be conceived to be <hi>Adiaphorous,</hi> and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; as that they may be at the will, and pleasure of Christians to observe, or not, without imputing any sanctity to them, or duty in the keeping of them holy; yet, if we remark the custome, and practice of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries of the Romish Church, in their strict injunctions upon the people to observe, yea, even idolize, and adore the commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Saints; and the great dishonour done thereby to the Blessed Trinity, in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Saints daies with the Observation of the Christians Sabbath, or Lords day; We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38165:12"/> certainly but conceive, it will be very dangerous, and destructive to the principles of Religion it self in tract of time; when as by experience we daily see, that custome in evil affords, and administers occasions of greater evils, and takes away at length the very sense, and apprehension of offending: And Satans Stratagems, in obstructing the propagation of the Gospel, have with more advantage prevailed, by instilling into mens minds the soporiferous, and drowsie opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of things indifferent in the Christian profession; than by his manifest oppugning of many damnable heresies against fundamental Truths.</p>
            <p>Upon the consideration whereof; and since that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> have with so much ardor, and zeal, not onely prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched for the observation of Holy daies; but at last kept, and observed such daies with much solemnity, contrary to the said Acts of our Colloquies, (being onely patronized by an assumed power of part of our Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, in opposition to our ancient, and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed Government by Colloquies; who by their own private act have usurped to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the same; and doe in their Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let justifie themselves therein:) And least the people of our Congregation should be infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38165:12"/> with such dangerous, licentious, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Doctrines; as have been within these three yeers delivered, partly by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and partly by Mr. <hi>Stouppe;</hi> (as shall be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately objected to the Readers judgement:) Therefore Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> as a faithful Pastor, held it his duty to oppose such Doctrines, delivered to his Flock, as might corrupt them, either in their principles of Faith, or dispose them to Libertinisme, and licentious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and so directly to instruct, and exhort them according to sound doctrine, and the word of God: Which was the first, and principal occasion, that hath caused all the ensuing, and future troubles, and contentions amongst us. And if he had not good ground so to doe, (upon consideration of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars,) let all impartial, and true hearted Christians judge. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>hath publickely asserted, That men may institute other memorials in the worship of God, besides the Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He hath preached against the Morality of the fourth Commandement, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine institution of the Lords day: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested much for Holy daies; saying, That Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cost was thrice Holy; and that there were three Holy daies of moral Right; one for God the Father, another for God the Son, and another for God the Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38165:13"/>3. <hi>That the Law was an Hypocrite: That there were Hypocrisies in the Law: That it is like a clock, that marks at six, and strikes twelve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That the Divel had a National, and Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomical Empire of death over the Nation of the Jewes; And that Christ himself was under that Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That Beleevers under the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had not the Spirit of Adoption; And much inveighed against that expression,</hi> That the Law is a School-master to bring us to Christ; <hi>and insisted to confute it, as a great Errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That good works go before Justification, aswell as follow after: and alledged many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that a man is saved by, and for his good works; and children are saved by the seed of those good works:</hi> with many others too long to enumerate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> in a Preparation-Sermon, for the observation of holy daies, 21 <hi>Decemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> 1656, took a Text on purpose, and forsook the ordinary Catechisme: Affirming, <hi>That since Bishops were put down, there hath been no Reformation in this Countrey. And if any did make a Sermon upon Holy daies, they will call them superstitious, and Idolaters; And if we make scruple to preach on Holy daies, we
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38165:13"/> shall scandalize the Churches of</hi> Geneva, <hi>and</hi> France; with many other unfit expressions, touching other matters also. All which shall be fully proved before a Colloquie of all our Churches; whensoever it shall please God to give them an opportunity of meeting in due order, and according to our Discipline, and Government.</p>
            <p>Upon these sad Occurrences, many irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar proceedings have been since transacted by our Consistory; who have unwarrantably, and Un-christian-like adhered to Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe;</hi> condemning rather Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> for preaching wholesome, and saving Doctrine; which they pretended, he did mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in confutation of his Colleagues, and for counterpointing of them: whereas it was, (and so they should have interpreted it, had they made use of any ingenuity,) for the building up of our Congregation in our most holy Faith: And thereupon they pretend to have passed these three following Acts, by them recited. <hi>pag.</hi> 4. for the peace, and quiet of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First, That the Pastours should promise to keep the affairs of the Consistory secret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Pastours should not preach one against the other; but if any found fault at the Sermon of his Colleague, he should ask him
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38165:14"/> satisfaction in private, or addresse himself to the Consistory; not undertaking of himself to confute the Doctrine, which he could not find agreeing to his sense.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Ministers should mutually ask, and give pardon for all offences.</hi> Which last was done upon an occasion of a difference between Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Delmey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Acts, <hi>the Pamphlettors pretend to be mild, and favourable to Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>and most just, and necessary: yet he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended never to submit unto them, calling them unjust, tyrannical, and devilish. And so,</hi> pag. 5, 6, <hi>they pretend to state, and set down Mr.</hi> Delmey<hi>'s several answers to each Act, and the Consistories debates with him thereupon.</hi> Which answers, (as they are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by themselves, if judiciously considered,) contain so much Charity, and Christian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the duty incumbent to a faithfull Pastor, (in respect either of his Cure, or himself,) That the future proceedings of the Consistory against him, must of necessity be construed, to be rather out of malice, and presumption, than upon any just cause of Censure: And that a Christian ought to obey God, according to his Word, rather than the Acts, and Injunctions of unreasonable men, we think no Judicious person will deny.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38165:14"/> And as <hi>Augustine</hi> saith of Ministers; <hi>Although they may do well themselves, and yet do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit things unlawful, they thereby consent to the Errors themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, it will not be impertinent, (in respect the Consistory, <hi>pag.</hi> 6, 7. pretend, <hi>that for Mr.</hi> Delmey<hi>'s non-submission to the said Acts they suspended him, first from his charge of Moderator, and then summoned him to appear before the</hi> Coetus <hi>of the strangers Churches in</hi> London, <hi>as the true, natural, and competent Judge, in such cases, (according to the Patent of</hi> Edward <hi>the sixt:)</hi> That we render to the Reader an exact account of our constant, and saepenumerous Applications to the Consistory, from our first sad sense of the Tendency of such Debates in our Church; as also of the several behaviours of the Consistory to us, and Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> and his comportment, and demeanour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, in as brief a manner, as the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of the matter will give way.</p>
            <p>But we shall first premise, That Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey</hi> did alwaies submit passively to the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Consistory, so far as the Word of God, and the Discipline or our Churches would give way; appealing onely to the Colloquie, as the supreme Judges in our Churches, (whither he was in the right, or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38165:15"/> wrong,) as our Discipline allowes.</p>
            <p>On the 19<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of <hi>December</hi> 1655. Many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families, (who had born Office in our Church,) appeared at the Consistory, and in an humble manner did remonstrate in writing, <hi>Their grief for the Contentions in the Church, rendring it in dislike to God, and all good men, and a scandal to the English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein they lived, Representing their Complaints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>should be permitted to preach for holy dayes, in favour of them, and such like doctrines against the Acts of our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies, and the practice, and Law of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That he should be permitted to preach doctrines, not conformable to the Word of God, without giving Christian satisfaction, when of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>should be censured for preaching on the</hi> 21<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>Section of the Catechism, touching Repentance, and on the fourth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Romanes v.</hi> 3. <hi>touching Atheisme, and threatned, to be interdicted the Pulpit, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Pastour,) contrary to the practice of our former Consistories, and Acts of Colloquies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Stouppe, <hi>should on that last fast day animate the Consistory, and the people against their Minister;</hi> desiring, <hi>that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38165:15"/> might be examined, and so ordered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed, that the Church might be satisfied accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods word, and the members united in peace, and concord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which being read, and debated privately by the Consistory, they returned answer by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> their President, <hi>That they refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the business to the Colloquie, which should meet</hi> 10 <hi>January following;</hi> And yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, the same time ordered, That publick preaching should be in <hi>Christmass</hi> holy-daies following, contrary to our Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The said tenth of <hi>January,</hi> Deputies of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches met in <hi>London,</hi> (called out of design at that extraordinary time by our Consistory, to infringe our Government, by endeavoring to conjoin them with the Dutch Colloquie in Synod:) Which the Deputies disagreeing to doe, and Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they would not act any thing for the Consistories advantage, and telling them they should not have their charges defrayed, nor sit any longer, (contrary to the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries own promise,) they dissolved: And so our complaints remained unreleeved.</p>
            <p>After this, our Consistory presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously sent a Narrative of the said Deputies proceedings, to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Dover;</hi> assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38165:16"/> thereby power over the Deputies of other Churches, contrary to our Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: Which the Minister of <hi>Dover</hi> carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over to <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> it was taken from him, and fell into Priests, and Papists hands, to the great Scandal of our Churches.</p>
            <p>Now by the way, to give the Reader some short account of the grounds, and manner of the Consistories making the said three Acts, let this Relation be considered. That Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> professing themselves enemies to Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> for his piety, and zeal, <hi>in refuting false, and erroneous Doctrines,</hi> upon pretence that he contradicted them; And absolutely designing with some of the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, to destroy the Government of all the French Churches by Colloquies, (contrary to their solemn promises to God, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, as before, and in this ensuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise will evidently appear;) They passed the first Act, contrary to our Discipline, meerly to injoin Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> by keeping their affairs se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, (which never was imposed upon any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor in our Churches,) to give them the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter advantage of carrying on their Design, in altering our Government, by Colloquies, to a <hi>Coetus</hi> of our Consistory, and the Dutch, (no Italian Minister being then in <hi>London.</hi>) Whereby they would have been Judges, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38165:16"/> parties in their own case; And none of our Members, that had been Officers, should have been enabled to prevent their Design: And moreover, they would have with the more confidence, and injustice, affronted Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> without hopes of redress: Which with his Christian Friends he had good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to obstruct; for that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> have so long, and often contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him, for the manner, (as they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,) of his Sermons, distorting, and wresting his words to other Senses, and Constructions. <hi>And Mr.</hi> Cisner <hi>hath spoken, and written, that Satan hadraised a great persecution against him by Mr.</hi> Delmey<hi>'s means. Mr.</hi> Stouppe <hi>hath frequently called him Lyar; and said, He was fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be in Bedlam, than in a Consistory. Mr.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Barr, <hi>(a present Elder,) hath also called him an Instrument of the Devil: And once swore by God, that either Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>should bowe, or be thrust out.</hi> And with many other uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, unchristian, and uncivil expressions, have they misdemeaned themselves towards him; that had not his piety, prudence, and patience concealed them; they would have made the Breaches far wider, than they have been in our Church.</p>
            <p>And upon the same ground to propagate their false and erroneous Doctrines, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38165:17"/> without reproof, they composed their second Act; To oblige Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> not to teach, and instruct his Congregation in the right way: for, being by the first Act obliged to keep all affairs secret; and by the second injoined not to dispute any thing, but in Consistory; it will of consequence be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that the poor Congregation should be perverted, and led into Errors, and false opinions by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> without any confutation, or exprobration thereof; to the hazarding of their Faith, and good consciences, and eternal confusion of their Souls; When as the Consistory have wholly inclined to M. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and M. <hi>Stouppe;</hi> as by common experience can be manifested by Mr. <hi>Jurion,</hi> Mr. <hi>De Fervacques,</hi> Mr. <hi>Beaumont,</hi> and seueral others.</p>
            <p>For their third Act, for the Ministers mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual asking, and giving pardon for all offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: It was made meerly to protect, and patronize Mr. <hi>Cisner;</hi> who by word, and writing, had unworthily dishonoured Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s deceased Father; who had been an eminent, and Godly Minister in our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and one of the Ministers of the late As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> insisting in the Consistory, to have his Fathers credit justly vindicated; (though as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38165:17"/> to himself the Pamplettors confess, he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave Mr. <hi>Cisner;</hi>) They nevertheless passed the matter over with too much partiality, and indignity, in respect of such a deceased Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Pastor. And in their Pamphlet, (as being ashamed of such injustice,) take no notice at all, what the matter was, that Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> should say; he had not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> but had been offended by him, and therefore could not ask him pardon.</p>
            <p>Upon all which, the courteous Reader may revolve, and consider; whether Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> hath not been hitherto much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, and attempted against to be insna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: yet for the greater elucidation of the truth, It will not be amiss, to offer to the Reader the three Engagements, and Recognitions; which Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and submitted to be obliged by before the Consistory, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I promise to keep the secrets of the Consistory, according to the Word of God, and the Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Also to abstain, as much as shall be possible to me, (through the grace of God,) to give any just cause of personal offence to any one in my Sermons: Provided, this be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38165:18"/> taken in such sense; as that I be not thereby restreined in my just liberty, to preach against all manner of Errors, and vices, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of persons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>In mainteining a good cause, I doe willingly acknowledge, that I may have failed some times, in saying too much, and some times in saying too little: For which I am sorry, and humbly crave pardon for it: Provided, this be taken in such sense; as that it be without prejudice to the good cause, which I am perswaded, I have mainteined, in opposing of Holy daies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greatest part of which Recognitions, and proposals the Pamphlettors admit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves: and whither they be not satisfactory, and sufficient, in reference to the Office of a godly Minister, is left to the Readers censure. Yet notwithstanding the interpositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the said Fathers of Families; Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s offers rejected; and his appeal to a Colloquie, according to our Discipline; And after, that the said Colloquie dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Inconsultâ materiâ,</hi> and without effect, after the tenth of <hi>January</hi> 1655: The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory of <hi>London</hi> took upon them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute anew, against Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> And without power, summoned him before a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38165:18"/>
               <hi>Coetus</hi> of the Dutch Church, and themselves; as <hi>pag.</hi> 7, 8, 9. they make a long relation, to which we referre the Reader. And whereas they say, <hi>That that</hi> Coetus <hi>was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies esteemed, the true, natural, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge of all the particular Churches, which compound it; And that the</hi> Coetus <hi>were going to pronounce the Sentence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation against Mr.</hi> Delmey; <hi>And passed such Acts, as they mention; To which they required Mr.</hi> Delmey's <hi>conformity, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission; which he refused, though advised otherwise by the Moderator of that Assembly:</hi> We shall give no answer thereunto, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a meer delusion. <hi>For as much, as the Consistory of the</hi> Dutch-<hi>Church in</hi> London, <hi>and the Moderator afore mentioned, the</hi> 23<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
               <hi>of</hi> August, 1657: <hi>have positively denyed, and disclaimed the matters touching them, in the said Pamphlet specified, as the same are therein stated, and denoted: Or that they undertook any such pretended power, to be Judges; Or went about to adjudge, or censure Mr.</hi> Delmey; <hi>Or laid any such charge, or injunction upon him; Or ever entred into, or intermedled with the merits of the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: But onely interposed, as friends, to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie, and moderate; And not as having any power to injoin, or command.</hi> And this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38165:19"/> they affirmed, and declared in presence of Mr. <hi>Houblon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jurion,</hi> Mr. <hi>John de Lilers,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Isaac le Gay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which passage, the Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may very well be perswaded, of what credit, and esteem the said Pamphlet, in the whole compilation thereof, ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted: And more particularly from this also, that the Pamphlettors would pretend, <hi>that a</hi> Coetus <hi>is impowered over the French Church in</hi> London, <hi>by the Patent of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of</hi> Edward the sixt, <hi>of the Church of the</hi> Germans, <hi>and other Strangers in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: Whereas in truth, in the whole body of that Patent, (as hereafter will appear,) there is not the least mention of any such power, granted to the Grantees, or Paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees; But they are generally left to their own proper Rites, and ceremonies, and their own proper, and peculiar Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Discipline: And as for the French Church in <hi>London,</hi> they have been for about these eighty yeers, governed apart from the Dutch, by Colloquies; compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Deputies of all the other <hi>French</hi> Churches in <hi>England,</hi> and their own; and in the interval of Colloquies, by their own proper Consistories; as by their books, and Registers will plainly appear.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:38165:19"/>
            <p>Whereas furthermore, the Pamplettors, (notwithstanding their egregious disinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity to assert that, which the Dutch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory themselves deny, as aforesaid,) do <hi>pag.</hi> 9.10. traduce Mr. <hi>Delmey, for sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Sermons, making Assemblies of his own to oppose their Government, and increasing his Outrages against the Consistory; though they offered him reconciliation, if he would accept their Articles, or those of the</hi> Coetus; <hi>And refusing both, they, (assembled with the Deacons,) suspended him from the Exercise of his charge, till he acknowledged his faults, and returned to his duty. And as if their proceedings were so just, and necessary, and without precipitation, hatred, or animosity against Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>they seem to appeal to all men.</hi> It will not therefore be irrequisite, If, (for the further demonstration of truth,) we give you a second Relation of the great care, and sollicitation of the aforesaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families, in applying to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory again for peace: Who 27 <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> 1655. presented another Paper to them, (Referring to their former Address 19. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> last before:) <hi>Wherein, they mention their being sent to the Colloquie by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, called</hi> 10 January, <hi>then last past: But that the Deputies, being come, (instead
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38165:20"/> of finding help,) they observed, they were hindred, that they could not form in Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie; and ever after the miseries of our Church were grown worse, and worse: So as, the Consistory had put by Mr.</hi> Blanchar, <hi>of his Office of</hi> Consolator, <hi>for having shewn to some person the writing, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented: And suspended Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>from his charge of</hi> President; <hi>because it was said, he was a Rebell against Ecclesiasticall Orders: Which, (were it true,) he might aswell, or better be suspended from his Ministery: Which increased their fears, that the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story desired to hunt him out of our Church: And they could not silently pass, that one had preached in Christmas holy daies; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their Complaints, and reasons to the contrary; which the Consistory resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at their former Application. Therefore from their sense of duty towards God, our Church, and themselves; and for discharge of their Consciences, they again signified, how grieved they were at heart for those dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders; And prayed them earnestly, to restore Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>to his President-ship, and Mr.</hi> Blanchar <hi>to his Comforter-ship; And sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly call a Colloquie, (it being the onely Remedy of all our differences:) Not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing the Consistory; but admonishing them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38165:20"/> of their duty. Yet though they were but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Members of the Church, (yet in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great Importance, according to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline,) the Members ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected; as having a just Liberty to represent their griefs, and seek their remedy. And in a Case extraordinary, (when the Pilot is ready to sink the Ship,) all within it are concerned to contribute for their safety; And therefore the said Fathers were resolved to seek the means, that the Colloquie be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and that suddainly, if the Consistory did it not: Desiring their present answer; And praying them in the fear of the</hi> Lord, <hi>to consider, and take the thing to heart; that they might all be reunited in a good, and holy peace, and concord, to aim altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Port, and Haven of Eternal sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which was read, and debated by the Consistory: And their answer returned by Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> President, taking several ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections to the Paper, and concluding, <hi>That if they endeavoured to call a Colloquie, the Consistory would hinder it, for the Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that might follow.</hi> Which they did accordingly, contrary to our Acts of Colloquie.</p>
            <p>For, the Church of <hi>Canterbury</hi> some few
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38165:21"/> daies after, (having the charge to call the next Colloquie, and the ordinary time for it, expiring in <hi>May</hi> following; and having occasion to settle a Minister in their Church;) wrote to the Church in <hi>London,</hi> to send their Deputies to <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> to compose a Colloquie there; But the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> inamicably, and uncharitably rejected the Colloquie, and the Consistory of the said Church also. Yet the Church of <hi>Canterbury</hi> used all means, that the Colloquie might meet, 12 <hi>May</hi> following: Upon which the Fathers of Families in <hi>London,</hi> waited the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that time, hoping a Colloquie might convene in an ordinary way: But by the Refractory, and unbrotherly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the said Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> all their, and our hopes were frustra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Yet, (notwithstanding all the afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned mediations for an orderly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, of all differences in our Church, applied to the Consistory; And their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against our Ecclesiastical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a Colloquie,) The Pamphlettors are so presumptuous to accuse Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> (who of right appealed from them to a Colloquie, as the natural, and supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38165:21"/> Judges of our Church,) <hi>for rebellion against Ecclesiastical order, and bold impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the sense, and practice of Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches.</hi> Whereas, (as before,) no Consistory, (being but subordinate,) can in reason be presumed to be equivalent to a Colloquie; which is the primitive power of our Church. And therefore the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlettors are very rash, and procacious, to adventure on a bold, and irregular assum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of power, to censure a Pastor of our Church, (Religious, and honest in his life, and conversation, as they by their Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let admit,) after that he hath appealed to a greater, and superintendent power: Nor is it, or can it be the sense, or practice of any Reformed Church, (especially of the Dutch Church;) who have so positively denyed, and renounced the Pamphlettors grand illusion, as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And not to trouble the courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with a long commentary, on <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. Wherein throughout, the Pamphlettors, (presuming to themselves an absolute, and well constituted power to censure Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> (which in common reason can never be admitted; doe solely begge the question, and by suppositive, and Hypothetical que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38165:22"/> descend ro <hi>positive,</hi> and <hi>categoricall conclusions;</hi> That because, they would have it so, therefore Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> is, and must needs be a Rebel against them. But as their charity is no more predicable, than their Logick, we think it impertinent to give a Response in this place; having in other parts of this Book, so fully answered them, and defended Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s Innocence, and our own: And therefore doubt not, but that the Christian, and impartial Reader, will candidly judge of all matters in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; When as he will plainly see, that the Pamphlettors have farced, and stuffed the said pages, with nothing but harsh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, Revilings, and Railings, ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming any sober, or sagacious Christian; Taking upon them a God-like power to judge of Mr. <hi>Delmey's</hi> very heart; In as much as, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. they arraign Mr. <hi>Delmey, as having a seared Conscience, and presuming somewhat to himself, to be more than a man▪</hi> And all this they inculcate, because he wil not submit to their private Acts, in a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, and cowardly way: And yet they, (without giving any satisfaction,) stand upon their own Justification, in high, and insulting Termes; As if we ought to admit, that they have done rightly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38165:22"/> notwithstanding that they have notorious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted against our Discipline, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>Moreover the Reader is advertised, how the Pamphlettors, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. <hi>carp, and fret, at some speeches of Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>in his Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; calling some of the Congregation, Saints; and Gods children; exhorting them not to agree with the wicked, and Reprobate; And saying once, if they preacht upon holy daies, they should scare all the good men out of the Church:</hi> What can any pious, or devout Christian except against such Phrases? when they are seconded by the Warrant of the holy Scripture: And were not the Pamphlettors pricked in Conscience with some guilt, or offence, they would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort such expressions upon their Christian brethren; who affirme, that with all mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Christian affection, they have merely insisted for, and indeavored the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the good order of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, according to their Discipline, and acts of Colloquies. And therefore, wel might Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> use his Phrase, (being but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatory, and that in private,) That by preaching on holy daies, (contrary to Acts of Colloquies,) they would scare those men, (that did well in standing to maintain those Acts,) out of the Church.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:38165:23"/>
            <p>And so in order of time, we shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to that, which the Pamphlettors, in <hi>pag.</hi> 21. account, as a very great wrong, and offence to them; <hi>That before they had interdicted Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>the exercise of his Ministery, he had caused a Petition full of false, and impudent accusations to be presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his</hi> Highness. As to which we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, (in the Faith of our Christian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession;) That Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> was cleerly, and absolutely free from the framing, or presenting of that petition, (for which we have very good, and eminent proofs:) And for the matter thereof, we avouch it to be true, and our complaint, and prayer just, and equitable; As it was presented to his <hi>Highness</hi> in the words following, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38165:23"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To his HIGHNESSE, The LORD PROTECTOR of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. The humble Petition of divers Fathers of Families, of the French Church <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in behalf of themselves, and many other Members,</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth:</opener>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Consistory of that Church, (against the mutuall Agreament of themselves, and the rest of the French Churches in <hi>England,</hi>) have introduced the Observation of holy daies; And tyrannically suspended Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (one of their Ministers,) from part of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38165:24"/> Office, for preaching against Holy daies, and Atheistical, and dangerous opinions, and for teaching the Doctrine of Repentance, and other Orthodoxe truths; Endeavouring to eject him out of his Cure; And upon unjust grounds, have debarred divers Members from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, to the great grief of your Petitioners.</p>
                        <p>That Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and the said Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, (being injuriously traduced,) have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to a Colloquie, of all the said French Churches, according to their right, and usuall way in such cases. And Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> (ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Ministers,) standing charged with false Doctrine, and dealing in his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterial charge; the said Consistory, and Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> have, and still do refuse to come to the tryal, and examination of a Colloquie, (though several times called,) and decline the Judgement thereof: Attempting to have all matters decided by themselves, and the Dutch Church in <hi>London,</hi> contrary to their Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Government; which was made by consent of all the French Churches.</p>
                        <p>Wherefore your Petitioners humbly pray your <hi>Highness,</hi> will be graciously pleased to Order; That a Colloquie of the said Churches may be convened with all speed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38165:24"/> in <hi>London;</hi> Impowering them fully to summon all parties, and witnesses, (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with such Books, and Papers, as shall be expedient.) And upon examination, and hearing, amicably to accord all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, (if they can;) or otherwise cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the particulars to your <hi>Highness,</hi> with their opinion; That by your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness power, and goodness, the said Church may be setled in good order, and peace.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioners, (as in duty bound,) shall pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>The Answer thereto.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Whitehall. <date>May <hi>26. 1656.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>His <hi>Highness</hi> leaveth the Petitioners to their former Liberties, and customes.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed. <hi>Nath. Bacon, Master of Requests.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38165:25"/>
            <p>Now, whither we had not just ground to address our selves to his <hi>Highness,</hi> (the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magistrate, and Protector of our Liberties, and Customes;) when we, and the other Churches were so unworthily slighted, and abused by the said Consistory; let the Judicious Reader upon all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misses determine. And had the Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettors had any Candor, or love of the truth, they would have related our Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion truely, and wholly: But doubtless be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conscious of their own misdeeds, yet desirous to abuse their Readers, by impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them, but part of our Petition; they thereby vainly conceived to suffocate our just cause, or impaire the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>And whither, (as the matter, and prayer of our Petition is just, and reasonable,) his <hi>Highness</hi> answer thereto, be not most graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and receptive; we submit also to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And moreover, the contents of our complaints in the said Petition, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Pamphlettors affirmations, that it is full of false, and impudent Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusations, as in their <hi>pag.</hi> 21 appears;) have been fully proved before the Referrees of his <hi>Highness,</hi> (being seven godly Ministers;) <hi>Who have also reported the same to his</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:38165:25"/> Highness, <hi>(after several meetings, and due Considerations by them had of the Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and proofs on both sides:) Certifiing, that the difference at first began in our Church, about the observation of holy daies; which for many years last past, have been disused, and laid aside by several Acts of our Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies; but were now of late introduced again by the Consistory, and Sermons preached pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely for, and on those daies, by Mr.</hi> Cis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Stouppe. And also the said Referrees have reported to his <hi>Highnesse, that Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>was censured in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, for preaching a Sermon against Will-worship, and the observation of Holy daies: For which he was publickly opposed by Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>in the Church before the Congregation; and was also censured for his Sermon of Repentance.</hi> All which matters are expressed in the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before-recited. And whither, (since they are so positively reported to his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> to be true,) the Pamplettors have not been very insolent, and unworthy to calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate us, as if we had falsely, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently accused them; let the Reader judge: but more especially, since that the said Referrees, in all the said proceedings doe conceive, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families have been greatly injured,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38165:26"/> and that the Acts of Consistory are not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by their Discipline, or any former Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidents, or Acts of Colloquie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After which, (Accounting his <hi>Highness</hi> answer a gracious confirmation of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Customes,) we sent a Copy of our Petition, and answer to the said Consistory of <hi>London;</hi> Desiring them fairly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>descend to a Colloquie: And we also sent another Copy to the Church at <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> who sent up Letters to the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>London;</hi> requesting also their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance: But they uncivilly refused; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning those Letters unopened, and reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Communion with that Church, or admission of a Colloquie, or any society with the said Fathers of Families of our own Church; out of contumacy, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, to alter the Government of all our said Churches.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding which Rejection, and haughty Comportment, the Fathers of Families, 8. <hi>Junii,</hi> 1656. addressed the third time to the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> and after Admittance, presented another Paper, to this effect:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:38165:26"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="paper">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sirs, and Honoured Brethren in Consistory;</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>VVE are sent unto you, from some Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families of this Church, to put you in mind, that we made our first Addresses to you, <hi>19. December,</hi> last, to make our Complaints, touching disorders in this Church: Upon which you sent us to the Colloquie, which was to assemble in the month of <hi>January</hi> following: Which Colloquie was hindred from forming, and returned without doing any thing, to our great grief. Seeing that, we presented our selves again, <hi>27 Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary;</hi> Praying you then to call again a Colloquie suddainly; Upon which we desired your Answer: which was, <hi>that you would endeavour to make opposition.</hi> Also see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Church, that had power to call a Colloquie, for the ordinary time in <hi>May</hi> last; and they also having found opposition, and received no assistance, or encouragement from this Consistory; but on the contrary found your hindrance; And by all means, you have laboured to avoid a Colloquie, and have endeavoured to carry all our differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to a <hi>Coetus,</hi> (after appeals made to a Colloquie:) And you are come to that, as to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38165:27"/> threaten some members of this Church, (who will not consent thereunto;) Carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your selves against our Discipline, and Government: Which proceedings, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others have much augmented our Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and disorders amongst us, and the other Churches of our language. Wherefore, we have been constreined to make our most humble Addresses to the <hi>Supreme Power,</hi> supplicating their help, to give us their Assistance; that our Government, (so laudable,) which hath been made by the Consent of all the Churches, might be preserved, and mainteined: Which hath been granted unto us, and our Liberties, and Customes ratified, with Honourable Encouragement; That (if neeed be,) we shall have again of their help, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance. Which having obteined, we have written a Letter to send to the Consistory, of the Church of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with the Answer of our <hi>Superiours:</hi> Praying them to convene a Colloquie, as soon as may be: But before the sending thereof, we have been sent unto this Company <hi>Wednesday</hi> last; And you being departed, We are now come, praying you to give your Assistance: that the Colloque may be so called; Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to determine our differences in the fear of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38165:27"/> God, according to our Discipline: But also by that means, all the Churches may be reunited in peace, and Concord; And that we might have no more Cause to make our Addresses, to no other; but to those, that have the Government of our Churches; and that all may be done to the Glory of God: The which we pray, and aspire for, and attend your Answer.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Which was read, and consulted by the Consistory; and answer returned, <hi>that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the said</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families <hi>had not shewed them the Petition, that they presented to the</hi> Lord Protector, <hi>They would give no Answer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore on Saturday, 14 <hi>Junii,</hi> 1656. divers of us again attended the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory with the Original Petition, and Copy thereof: And two of us were called in, and that Copy left in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory: When, we prayed their Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to call a Colloquie, as afore time: <hi>But they would give us no answer, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred us till Wednesday following.</hi> At which time, some of us were sent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire their Answer; <hi>Which was, that they could give no answer, till they did see the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38165:28"/> Original Petition.</hi> Which, the time before was ready to be presented: But then, they required it not: And now, meerly to procrastinate, and delay us in our Request, they demand it: Supposing, (as well they might, and indeed so it was,) that it was not then brought. By which Evasions, and Tergiversations, the Reader may pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably discerne, what inclinations the said Consistory have had, (according to their Christian duty,) to unity, and peace: And that they rather sought to propagate, and nourish dissention, and discord, to the trouble, and vexation of all our Churches.</p>
            <p>And that it was so, is evident; For that the Consistory, (apprehending his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> had given no other answer, then as aforesaid,) presumed, (as they often decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themselves,) that he would not further intermeddle in the business: And therefore, (being opposed by some Elders, &amp; Deacons,) they discharged an Elder, and rejected some Deacons out of the Consistory; Four whereof desisted to execute their Offices: And all was, because they disavowed their unjust proceedings against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> in putting him out of the Consistory: The four Deacons making their protests, and appealing to the next Colloquie, according
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38165:28"/> to our Government. And because they would not retract their appeals; they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed them of their offices, and elected a new Elder, and four Deacons in their stead; on purpose to corroborate their faction, and carry on their designs with the more faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but greater partiality, and injustice.</p>
            <p>For soon after, in an <hi>extrajudicial,</hi> and <hi>unheard of</hi> way, the said Consistory conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> before the people, (after he had appealed to a Colloquie, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said;) <hi>And there, in a most unlawfull, and usurped manner arraigned him; Charging him with several things, by the space of two hours, for which he had appealed:</hi> To which for some time, (for the clearing of his own innocence, and full satisfaction of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation) he insisted to make his Defence; desiring first to have Liberty of prayer for Gods assistance; which was denyed him: And at length, being interrupted by Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and evening approaching, Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> promised, in the Consistories name, <hi>That the meeting should be continued two half daies longer, and Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>should have no wrong, but be free to make his Defence.</hi> Whereupon for that present, the Assembly adjourned: At whose departure, the people, (disgusted with their proceedings,) called
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38165:29"/>
               <hi>with a loud voice, and much importunity, for a</hi> Colloquie, <hi>a</hi> Colloquie. And the next morning, the Consistory met again, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their Resolution, shut up the Church Doors, and broak their promise, made the last night; Whereby they obstupated, and prevented Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> from making, his Defence, and purging his innocence before the Congregation to this day.</p>
            <p>And the Consistory perceiving the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people, that they could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, or deceive them; who utterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned, and abhorred their proceedings, challenging their Natural rights, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes to be governed by Colloquies: Thereupon in a short time after, and in a clandestine manner, they called Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> to the Consistory; And by their own usurped, and unlawfull power, (After his Appeal, as aforesaid,) suspended him from his Ministery in that Church: And the next Lords day published his Suspension, and openly read many unjust charges against him; <hi>Threatning the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (if they were not peaceable,) they would complain against them to the Magistrate.</hi> Which action is so <hi>monstrous,</hi> and horrible, that it is without <hi>Parallel,</hi> and <hi>example</hi> in all the <hi>Reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:38165:29"/>
            <p>The 22<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of <hi>June,</hi> 1656 about 100. mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the French Church <hi>London,</hi> in the forenoon, presented themselves to the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story; 4 whereof desired entrance, but 2 only were admitted, and read a paper, as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="paper">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sirs, and honoured Ministers, and Elders.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>SEeing the proceedings, that you hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (our faithfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour;) we have thought it to be equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to present unto you our grief, and sorrow, that you have made in us, having interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him from the Pulpit. We cannot conceive, but you have done that unjustly: Being a business of such importance, It ought to have been ended by a Colloquie, according to the Discipline of our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: It being not convenient, that you should be Judges, and Parties in a difference of such consequence. Therefore <hi>Sirs,</hi> We pray you, (in the Name of God,) that you would establish him in his Charge, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to right, and reason: Fearing, that it happen, that the Church do become torne, and in great scandal to the Nation, and to our Adversaries. <hi>Which being declared to the Consistory, they put them off till
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38165:30"/> the afternoon; who then attending, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory dismist them without any answer; as they had uncivilly done at other times.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Wherefore, 25</hi> Junii <hi>1656, divers other Fathers of Families of our Church, went to the Consistory, and declared themselves in these words,</hi> viz.</p>
                        <p>We do here appear for our selves, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fathers of Families, for to represent unto you; that we doe disapprove of all your proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, done against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (our faithfull Minister;) having interdicted him from the exercise of his charge, against our Discipline. Therefore, We do make our Protest against your proceedings; making our appeal to a Colloquie to have our right.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Consistory nevertheless, being the more <hi>obdurate,</hi> and <hi>immollescent,</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all the former Overtures, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses;) Therefore, for the peace of our Church, and preservation of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, against injurious, and obstinate Infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and invaders; We were again constrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned most humbly to resort to the justice, and clemency of his <hi>Highness,</hi> by another Petition, in these words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:38165:30"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To his HIGHNESSE, The LORD PROTECTOR of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. The humble Petition of divers <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> of the French Church <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> in behalf of themselves, and many other Members,</head>
                        <opener>Sheweth:</opener>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat many differences arising in that Church, your Petitioners made their humble Addresses to your <hi>Highness,</hi> the <hi>26, May</hi> last: And thereupon your <hi>Highness</hi> was graciously plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, to leave your Petitioners to their former Liberties, and Customes: Which was made
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38165:31"/> known to the Consistory of the French Church in <hi>London,</hi> by delivering them a copy of the said Petition, and also unto the Church of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi> Which Church, and your Petitioners, (having made their endeavours thereupon for a Colloquie,) have been rejected by the said Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story: And in opposition to your Highness said Grant, they have (after an Appeal made to Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie by Consent,) without power, or legal tryal, suspended Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> (our Godly Minister,) from his Ministerial charge; to the great grief, and disturbance of the Godly members of the said Church.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, your Petitioners humbly pray, that to the former Grant, it may be added, That a Colloquie may be called; As in their former Petition is prayed: And in the mean time, Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> may be restored to his Ministery in that Church.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioners, (as in duty bound,) shall pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>The Answer thereto.</head>
                        <p>His <hi>Highness</hi> is pleased to Grant the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners the Liberty of a Coloquie, according to the Prayer of the Petition.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>3.</hi> Julii, <hi>1656.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Signed. <hi>Jo: Thurloe, Secretary of Estate,</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38165:31"/>
            <p>Soon after, the said second Original Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as also the first, and a copy of the last,) was presented to the said Consistory, and that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py left with them: And being desired to call a Colloquie according to his <hi>Highness</hi> Grant, they directed us to withdraw: And afterwards by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> (then President,) returned us answer, <hi>that they would give answer in time, and place.</hi> After which also, a Letter was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Consistory at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> by divers of our Fathers of families, &amp; sent with a copy of the said second Petition, and Order of his <hi>Highnes.</hi> Upon w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg>, that Consistory sentletters to all the <hi>French Churches</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> to meet in Colloquie, in <hi>London,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2 <hi>August,</hi> following.</p>
            <p>Yet the Ministers, and some Elders of the Consistory in <hi>London</hi> opposed; refusing to submit to a Colloquie, or to give any answer to the Letters from <hi>Canterbury;</hi> (who then had the immediate power to call the Colloque;) otherwise, then to return them again; rejecting the Consistory of that Church, &amp; the Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie also; out of a wilful rebellion against our Discipline, &amp; Government. And the more to manifest, and declare their pride, and ambition, and hatred towards their Brethren, they bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempted to prefer the ensuing Petition to his <hi>Highness:</hi> The body, and prayer whereof, shall (after the Readers view, and perusal) be anatomized, and dissected.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:38165:32"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To his HIGHNESSE, The LORD PROTECTOR of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions thereunto belonging. The humble Petition of the <hi>Ministers,</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> of the French Congregation, <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Sheweth;</opener>
                        <p>THat the Petitioners, and their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours have a long time enjoyed, the free Exercise of the reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion; and have been governed in peace, and order, by an auncient, and laudable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:38165:32"/> Discipline, used amongst them, founded on the Charter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth: (the copy whereof is annexed:) which Charter, as will appear, (in case of differences arising be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them,) impowereth, and constituteth a <hi>Coetus</hi> of all Strangers Churches in <hi>London,</hi> to decide such differences: And the same in such case hath been accordingly practiced heretofore, (as by certificate of the <hi>Coetus,</hi> also annexed, may appear:) Whereupon in some late differences, arising between the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners, one Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and some few of their Members, (persons of unquiet spirits,) without any other just cause, or Offence; the Petitioners, according to the constitution of their said Discipline, have sought, and desired the said Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> to referre the said differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to a <hi>Coetus,</hi> having also sought all means of Reconciliation: Which have been rejected by them, (as by Certificate annexed appeareth;) Which they all along declining, and calling for a Colloquie; your Petitioners, for the peace of the Church, have yielded to them, and at their own charges convened a Colloquie: But at their sitting, it was found by some of the members thereof, that there were many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct, and undue courses, taken to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then their Faction: So that some of the said Colloquie desired to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38165:33"/> as not being able to sit any longer, with such factious, and partiall persons. And yet it is so, (may it please your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi>) that the said turbulent, and restless persons, having, (by two several Petitions, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting many false, and scandalous Accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,) obteined an Order from your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> for the Liberty of a Colloquie, of the said partial Members, before justly excepted against; Which, if not prevented, will instead of effecting your <hi>Highness</hi> pious intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in making an Amicable end of Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, make the Breach wider, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, to the utter ruine of the said French Congregation.</p>
                        <p>It is therefore most humbly prayed; That your <hi>Highnesse</hi> will be gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleased, to leave the Petitioners to their auncient Liberties, and Customes; Which is, (in case of Difference,) to Referre to a <hi>Coetus.</hi> Otherwise that your <hi>Highnesse</hi> will Order, That accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their <hi>Discipline,</hi> (As by Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate hereunder annexed,) the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie</hi> of the <hi>Dutch Churches</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> may be joyned with the <hi>French,</hi> to compose a <hi>Synod,</hi> of all the Strangers Churches, (the said <hi>French
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:38165:33"/> Colloquie</hi> consisting, but of a few persons, and some of them partial;) It being the onely way to decide the depending Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>And your Petitioners shall pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                           <signed>Signed.
<list>
                                 <head>Elders.</head>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>D. Boucquet,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Paul D'obey,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Peter Caulier,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Peter Bar.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <signed>Signed.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Cisner,</hi> Pastor.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Stouppe,</hi> Pastor.</item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>The Answer thereto.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Whitehall. <date>Julii <hi>12. 1656.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>His <hi>Highness</hi> leaveth the <hi>Colloquie</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed if they please; and (if cause shal then appear,) from what shall be by them done, his <hi>Highness</hi> will give redress, such as shall be just.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed. <hi>Nath. Bacon, Master of Requests.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:38165:34"/>
            <p>By the contents of which Petition, and his <hi>Highness</hi> Answer thereto, we appeal to the Courteous Reader; whither the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, (who were but a part of the said Congregation,) are not by their own shewing, <hi>rebellious, and disobedient to, and against our Ecclesiastical Government.</hi> And have (as much as in them lay,) endeavoured to abuse his <hi>Highness,</hi> by suggesting, that a <hi>Coetus</hi> of all the Strangers Churches in <hi>London,</hi> is impowered, and constituted to decide their differences, by the Charter of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth: Whereas by the very thing it self, there is no such matter, (as is before expressed,) the words of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent being,) <hi>That the Patentees be suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely, and quietly to have, enjoy, use, and exercise their own proper Rites, and Ceremonies, and their own proper, and peculiar Ecclesiastical Discipline.</hi> Nor is there in that Patent, the least shadow of the constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Coetus;</hi> Our Government being intrinsecally within our selves, of the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral French Churches in <hi>England;</hi> And so hath been for about these eighty yeers: and no way commixed with the Dutch, or any other Strangers Churches. Nor doe we contest for any more Liberty, then what hath been for so many Succession of years accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38165:34"/> In so much that we have had 29 Colloquies of all our Churches, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion immerged: Of which the Reader will have a more exact account in this Treatise. And if Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> or any other of our Church, should have consented to have any difference decided, by any other power, then our Colloquie; certainly they must needs have contracted a very heavy guilt upon their Consciences; When as we are all obliged by solemn promisses, in the presence of God, to maintein our Discipline, and Government, as it hath been for so many years established in our Churches.</p>
            <p>And as to the Colloquie, mentioned in the said Petition, which convened 10 <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> 1655. We have given the Reader a full account before; How that by the undue practises of the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> they were dissolved without acting any thing at all. And had not our Petitions been worthy of reception, We conceive, his <hi>Highness</hi> would not have been so fauourably pleased to answer them, by granting our Requests; and in plain words to deny the Consistories Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by confirming ours therein also: as by his <hi>Highness</hi> Answer may appear. And to pass by those Petitioners hard Censures, and expressions of us, and their endeavours to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38165:35"/> have a Synod of the Dutch, and French Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies in <hi>England;</hi> because they pretend, the French Colloquie consists but of few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, some whereof are partiall; We shall onely intimate to the Reader, the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries grand defection from their Brethren; And positively to assert, That there are now more Deputies in capacity, to meet in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie of the French Churches in <hi>England,</hi> then formerly were, or could be assembled: In respect our Churches are increased, to almost double the number, which was about 20, or 30 yeers agone.</p>
            <p>And we shall herein further demonstrate, and prove, that the commixing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining of a Synod, composed of the Dutch Colloquie, and the French, (in the prayer of the said Petition mentioned, to be according to our Discipline;) is altogether inconsist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with, and different from our Discipline: And that the Churches of the Dutch, and French Nations, are not all the Strangers Churches now in <hi>England;</hi> (as the said Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners pretend. Whereby we conceive, that the Reader will positively conclude, that the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> hath prevaricated, and again, (as they did before concerning the <hi>Caetus,</hi> and the Patent of Edward the sixt,) endeavoured to misinform his <hi>Highness;</hi> And
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:38165:35"/> upon consideration of our proofs, and asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will benignely interpret our proceedings, in labouring to conserve our own Discipline, and Government.</p>
            <p>But as touching the Certificate, so often mentioned, and repeated in the said Petition, to be given by the <hi>Coetus;</hi> The same is, and hath been so privately kept, and concealed from us by the Petitioners, and their party: That for as much as we have had no Copy thereof: We can give no Answer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>But to continue a Method, and Series of transactions, the Reader shall understand, that after the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> did preferre the last recited Petition to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and were repulsed; They nevertheless at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted 6. <hi>August,</hi> 1656, to misinforme his <hi>Highness</hi> again: And therefore Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> with six Elders, and four Deacons of the Consistory, (unexpected by the Fathers of Families,) had audience before his <hi>Highness</hi> at <hi>Whitehall:</hi> Where, four of the said Fathers, happening to be by Providence, were also admitted to his <hi>Highness</hi> presence: Before whom, Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> complained against the appointed Convention of the Colloquie, 22. <hi>August</hi> following, <hi>Charging the Deputies with partiality, and pressing with much importunity,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38165:36"/> that the differences might be decided by the</hi> Dutch, <hi>and themselves in</hi> Coetus, <hi>(as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Judges:)</hi> But his <hi>Highness,</hi> hearing our Defence, <hi>Ordered that the Colloquie should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed; and if they could not end the differences, He would appoint ten, or twelve Godly Divines, of the</hi> English <hi>Nation to determine the same:</hi> Unto which, (being by Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi>'s own proposition,) both parties submitted. But the Consistory being still restless, and design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (as much as in them lay,) either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the meeting of the Colloquie, or ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and our selves, to them, and all the world, as culpable, and offensive per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; Did therefore publish in French, and English, (without the consent of the Dutch Consistory,) the said Libellous Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</p>
            <p>And since we have used all the aforesaid means, for a Reconciliation between the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, and our selves, (as by all the fore-reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted passages, and papers will appear,) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Government of our Churches, and for the preservation thereof; And if the Reader please to consider our Petitions to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and the Petition of the Consistory, and their Actings, and Obstructions endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured against us; It will manifestly appear to his Judgement, that we have onely insisted
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38165:36"/> to maintein our Church Government, and to keep unity, and order therein; And whither the Pamphlettors be any better, than such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as they, <hi>pag.</hi> 22. doe labour to disprove themselves to be, <hi>viz. Abominable persons, and Libertines:</hi> When as, they did actually suspend Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> for preaching against ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daies, and for the Doctrine of Repentance, as is before proved in the Report to his Highness before mentioned: And when as <hi>pag.</hi> 24. they in some manner confess, <hi>that Holy daies were abolisht by our Colloquie in the year</hi> 1644. Which we affirme was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and also by another in the year, 1654.</p>
            <p>At all which unreasonable proceedings of the Consistory, the Reader shall not need to admire; if he seriously consider, with what disrespect, and unnatural declension, they desert our Government by Colloquies, so long used, and continued in our Churches; So that in their Pamphlet, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. they doe onely, and that very carelesly, make mention of a Colloquie; As if it were but some small part, or rather none at all, of our Church-Government, or not worthy to be mentioned with respect; And that although Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey</hi> appealed to a Colloquie in 1655; And because, <hi>it never was held; therefore
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38165:37"/> his appeal should be void:</hi> Which is a Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent so incongruous, and inconsistent to, and with the natural constitution of all Courts, and Conventions for Appeals, as also of our Colloquies themselves, that it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in equity, or good Conscience: For then it would evene, that if there should be a Determination, and cessation of Appeals by the Non-convention of the persons, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in chief to judge; the Consciences, as well as the Estates of the Appellants, should be subjected to the fatal inconveniences of unjust, and arbitrary Sentences, by a meer circumstance of time. And whereas they men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. <hi>That in the intervals of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, the power of Censures should be in the Consistory;</hi> It is objected to the Readers Judgement, how weak, and unreasonable their inference is: As if the general standing Rules of our Discipline, and acts of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, had not provided for the good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churches, in the vacancy of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies; But that yet, the power of judging should be left to the discretion of the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, after an appeal made from them to a Colloquie. Whereby it will not, nor can be denyed; But that the Consistory have been more willing, and propense to usurpe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves a power, and Jurisdiction over Mr.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:38165:37"/>
               <hi>Delmey,</hi> and others; which did not, nor doth it belong to any others whatsoever, but to our Colloquies themselves; As hereafter will more fully appear.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the last page of their Pamphlet, the Authors <hi>appeal to their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Judgement, whither upon Consideration of their Proceedings, they will not judge Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>to be the Author of all the troubles of our Church, and that they have most justly suspended him from the exercise of his charge amongst them, for the Causes by them specified:</hi> We likewise fly to the Judgement of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial men; whither, upon their serious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise, and perusal of this Tractate, and our manifest producing, and stating our passages, and papers, from the first unhappy contest, to this present; As before, and hereafter they will plainly see; That the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> have designed any thing more, then to advance themselves, (contrary to our Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,) into a Superiority above the common order, and custome of their Brethren of the other Churches: And out of a Spirit of arrogance, and contempt of them, do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>esteem, and undervalue them, as poor, and of little number, and accompt in this Nation: Whereas we affirme again, that we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more in number, and to be considerably
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38165:38"/> acccompted, then at present: as hereafter will also more plainly appear.</p>
            <p>Now in the last place, we find an <hi>Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix</hi> made to the said Pamphlet in English; Wherein the Consistory have been as disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous, and partial, as they have been in all the premisses, submitted to publique Construction: And they therein set down, under a <hi>glossy Title, Acts of the Colloquie of the French Churches assembled at London, August,</hi> 22. 1656. And at a morning Session, Friday <hi>September</hi> 12. to be made for the composure of our affairs: But in respect Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> rejected the sentence of the Colloquie, he had himself desired with so much ardor; and proceeded more than ever in clamors, and Calumnies against the Consistory; They therefore divulged those Acts: For ground whereof, It is pretended, that the Assembly seeing, that after their often exhortations to Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> to appear, and complain against the Church of <hi>London;</hi> he persisted obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately not to own the Colloquie, (though he promised submission thereto;) they thereupon proceeded, as the Consistory had before done against him. To which it is answered, That as the Consistory had all along be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, extrajudicially acted against Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey;</hi> So likewise did not those persons, by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38165:38"/> the unfitting practices of the Consistory, permit the Colloquie to constitute orderly, and as of ancient, and common right, they ought to have done. Nor do the Pamphlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors assert, that it was a Colloquie according to the Orders, and directions of his <hi>Highness,</hi> and Discipline of the Churches; (there being but two lawful Deputies to compose the same, As further will be evidenced:) Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, that in all the Series of the said Pamphlet, the <hi>Authors</hi> before presume to take upon themselves an absolute, and independ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent power to censure Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> by part of their Consistory, of themselves Simply, and divided; Now, the Reader may observe, that for the justification of themselves against Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> the <hi>Authors</hi> solely resort to, and build upon the Acts, pretended to be well made by that Assembly; although they were never regularly constituted.</p>
            <p>And next, we shall offer to the Readers Judgement, the Act of Discipline of all the French Churches in <hi>England:</hi> which now stands in force, and ought to be observed by them: The words whereof are, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38165:39"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="act">
                        <head>Of Colloquies, and Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies Generall.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>FOR the better mainteining of purity of life, and Doctrine, and together, Order, and union of the Churches; There shall be from year to year, or at other convenient time, one Assembly of all the Deputies of all the</hi> French Churches, <hi>that are in this Kingdom. And every Church shall send one Minister, and one Elder, furnished with Memorials, and Instructions, approved, and signed by the Consistory. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, without taking away the Liberty of the Minister, and Elder to propound of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, what they shall think expedient.</hi> These are the very words of the Discipline: Which will evince the truth, That that Assembly 22 <hi>August,</hi> 1656. were not a lawful Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie; And therefore, and upon the ground of the said Act of our Discipline, The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Families of the French Church <hi>London,</hi> in behalf of themselves, and many other Members, humbly petitioned <hi>his Highness the</hi> Lord Protector, <hi>in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, viz.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <q>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:38165:39"/>
                           <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                              <body>
                                 <div type="petition">
                                    <opener>
                                       <salute>Shewing;</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                    <p>THat your Petitioners have formerly made their humble Addresses to your <hi>Highness,</hi> in behalf of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (their faithful, and Godly Minister,) who is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly suspended from his Ministery in that Church; and also in behalf of divers members thereof: And thereupon your <hi>Highness</hi> graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously referred all differences, to a Colloquie of all the French Churches: And upon hearing, both parties, confirmed it; Proposing, that if an end was not made by the Colloquie, that your <hi>Highness</hi> would appoint ten, or twelve Godly Divines of this Nation, to make a final De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination. To which all parties consented.</p>
                                    <p>Since which, all endeavours have been made to call a Colloquie of all the French Churches in the Nation, according to your <hi>Higness</hi> said Grant: All appeared: Two Deputies of each Church were sent: The Deputies of three Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches first arrived, (being sixe persons:) Four of them onely assumed the power of a Colloquie, though not all capable to sit in Colloquie; Neither have they formerly: And after the two other Churches were admitted Judges, they deprived them from acting: And several times refused to call the other Churches absent, (as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38165:40"/> (And when they came, rejected them also, (except those of <hi>Dover:</hi>) Albeit one of them was a Delinquent in Armes, and departed the City upon your <hi>Highness</hi> last <hi>Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> And thereby, five persons onely, assumed to make a Colloquie, contrary to our Discipline: By combination with some of the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> (also disaffected,) that thereby they might keep all power in themselves; The better to maintein their unjust proceedings, formerly complained of; And the more to oppress Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (by engaging him against his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,) and others, who stand well affected to Reformation; In contempt of your <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> Order, and Proposals: Which they have disobeyed; and questioned your power, by Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring some for submitting thereunto: On purpose to frustrate your pious Inclinations to Justice, and peace.</p>
                                    <p>Which irregular proceedings, have been dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approved of by the Deputies of the three other Churches, (being sixe persons;) As by their Certificate annexed may appear; and also by the Consistory of the Church in <hi>Norwich;</hi> (As by their Letter annexed appeareth;) Who sent two of those five Deputies, that irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly acted, as aforesaid: Whereby no Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie hath been convened, according to your <hi>Highness</hi> Order, and the Discipline of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38165:40"/> Churches; and thereby no end of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences is made.</p>
                                    <p>Wherefore Your Petitioners humbly pray your <hi>Highness</hi> graciously to Order, that such a Number of Godly Divines, of this Nation, (As Your <hi>Highness</hi> shall think fit,) may hear, and determine the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences; As was submitted unto before Your <hi>Highness:</hi> Impowering them to summon all parties, and witnesses, with such Books, and Papers, as shall be expedient; That Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and the Members well affected, may not be oppresse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap> in their Consciences; But be protected from Injury, and enjoy the <hi>Gospell</hi> in its purity, and the Church setled in peace.</p>
                                    <closer>
                                       <signed>
                                          <hi>And your Petitioners, (as in duty bound,) shall ever pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                                    </closer>
                                 </div>
                              </body>
                           </floatingText>
                        </q>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:38165:41"/>
            <p>Here followeth the Certificate of the sixe Deputies, (in the said Petition mentioned,) Translated out of the Originall in French, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <head>London, the 18<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of September, 1656.</head>
                        <p>VVE under-written <hi>Ministers,</hi> and <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> Deputed from three of the <hi>French Churches</hi> here in <hi>England;</hi> namely, of <hi>Thorney Abbey, Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Sant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoff;</hi> Who have endeavoured to constitute a compleat <hi>Colloquie,</hi> of the Deputies of all the <hi>French Churches</hi> within this Nation; to end, (through the help of God,) the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some differences of the <hi>French Church</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and to establish in it a good, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent peace: But that taking no effect; (though all the Deputies of all the said Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, were at the same time in the said City,) being met together; And having also in our company, Mr. <hi>Crespine,</hi> (lately one of the Ministers of the Church of <hi>Canterbury:</hi>) And being desired to give our Advice, and Sense, (according to the Word of God, the Rule, and practice of the Reformed Churches, and specially, of the <hi>French Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> in this Nation,) Upon several difficulties,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38165:41"/> and Questions, propounded to Us; In all Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and sincerity, have answered: as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,</p>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>Whither a Consistory have in it self, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and power, to Interdict their Pastor, from the Exercise of his Charge: And to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish such an interdiction to the People; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling before hand, two, or three Ministers, (not suspected,) to help the said Consistory; especially, when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e is nothing against the life, and Doctrine of the Minister.</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>We answer, That according to the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Reformed Churches, a Consistory hath not that power, and Authority to interdict their Pastour, from the exercise of his Charge, for any fault whatsoever; without the help of two, or three Pastors, (not suspected;) much less, to publish the said interdiction; special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when he hath appealed to a Colloquie; which ought to determine differences, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ended in the Consistory. Now, the Interdiction of a Minister, is one of the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiest Difficulties, and wherein a Consistory ought not to precipitate it self. Lastly, there being
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38165:42"/> nothing against the life, or Doctrine of the Minister: And having appealed from the Sentence of the Consistory to the Colloquie: It is evident, he cannot be condemned of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against Ecclesiasticall Order. And that there is no sufficient Cause of interdiction, We have shewed this by Rule, and Example, in our ancient Colloquies.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>If we can allow of a Consistories gathering of the people together, to dishonor their Pastour, and make him contemptible amongst them.</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>We answer, that such a kind of proceeding is altogether unheard of in the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. That it is altogether contrary to Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; which doth not permit the debates of Consistory to be divulged to the multitude: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing also, the whole matter was referred to the Colloquie; the judgement whereof was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. Adde, that this is enervating, and takeing away the whole efficacy of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of the said Pastour, before a finall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And against Charity to spread the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills, (if any there were,) And to cause it to break out beyond its limits, instead of covering it.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>If a Colloquie, (being appointed by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:38165:42"/> Magistrate, for the deciding of certain differences, arisen in a Church, between two several parties;) one of the parties doth well to print a Book, with an intent to publish it in time, to stain, and blemish the reputation of the other party; before the decision of the said Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie.</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>We answer, That this kind of proceeding is much more to be rejected, and blame-worthy, than the former: For it tends to the defaming of persons throughout the whole world; yea, even amongst Infidels, and Enemies of the Church of <hi>Christ;</hi> and to fill all with scandals, and open the mouth of Adversaries to evil speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It is against all charity, and Piety; telling the debates of Brethren in <hi>Gath,</hi> and to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish them in the streets of <hi>Askelon:</hi> To the end, that the Daughters of the Philistines may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, and the Daughters of the uncircumcised triumph.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>If a Consistory may condemn their Pastour for his manner of preaching, without specifying wherein?</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>Such a general Condemnation, without specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, taketh away from the Pastor, the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ans of defending himself, or correcting hims<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>lf, in case, he hath failed.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <pb n="72" facs="tcp:38165:43"/>
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Whither these Propositions,</hi> A Minister must not alwaies preach the threats of the Law: And Ministers ought some times to preach the Threats of the Law, and some times the Promises of the Gospell, <hi>be contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>It is clear, there is no contradiction between them; and that they perfectly agree together.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>Whither it falling out to treat of the one, and twentieth Section of the <hi>Catechisme,</hi> where it is said, <hi>That God will not be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved according to our Phantasie, but his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure:</hi> It be not convenient to speak against humane Traditions, and voluntary service?</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>It is very requisite to be done; And this is onely to treat of the Subject of the Section.</p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="question">
                           <head>Question.</head>
                           <p>The Churches being seven, and there being but four met, (whereof the one is party,) And the other three remaining have but five Votes;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38165:43"/> Because one of the said Churches hath been deprived of one of her votes; Whither such a Company ought to be held for a lawfull Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, to decide differences of great difficulty; especially, when against the ordinary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, they have refused to write to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches absent?</p>
                           <div type="answer">
                              <head>Answer.</head>
                              <p>It is the Practice of our Churches, when they are met, to write to the Churches absent, to induce them to send their Deputies; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when Businesses are of great weight. And seeing, there never were more Churches of our Language in this Countrey, then now: And never a lesser Company of <hi>Deputies,</hi> then at this time, to compose a Colloquie: We judge, that such a small number of persons, ought not to have undertaken the decision of such difficulties, as did offer themselves; without endeavouring by their Letters, to strengthen themselves with the Deputies of other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: And when those Deputies were arrived, they ought not to have refused to adde them to their company; To the intent, they should together compose a Colloquie of the <hi>Deputies</hi> of all the Churches, of our Language in this Countrey.</p>
                              <pb n="74" facs="tcp:38165:44"/>
                              <p>Having seen the printed Acts of the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of the <hi>Coetus</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> (unto which Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> hath declared himself, not able to acquiesce,) And the profers in writing made by the said Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> drawing neer the said Acts: We judge, that it was a great wrong, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to him by the Consistory, to interdict him of the exercise of his ministery; By reason that he could not acquiesce in the said Acts: And so to put that dishonour upon him, and procure that Damage to the Church.</p>
                              <p>We judge also, That the said French Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> hath failed in setting up the publick exercises on Holy daies; Seeing, that is forbidden to all the Churches of our Language, in this Country, by our Colloquies from the year, <hi>1644.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <head>Signed.</head>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Edward le Keux,</hi> Elder, and Deputy of the Church of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Guilaim Rys,</hi> Elder, and Deputy of the Church of <hi>Thorney Abbey.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John le Heucq,</hi> Deputy of the Church of <hi>Santhoff.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <head>Signed.</head>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ezechiel Daunois,</hi> Minister of the holy Gospel, in the French Church of <hi>Thorney Abbey.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Philip le Keux,</hi> Pastor, deputed from <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>John de Kerhuel,</hi> Pastor, deputed from <hi>Santhoff.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38165:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Here followeth, also the Letter from the Consistory of the Church of</hi> Norwich, <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the said Petition, Translated also out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Norwich, 15 September. 1656.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sirs, and honoured Brethren,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VVE are informed, You have refused to call the Deputies of the other French Churches to you in Colloquie; and that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> have but one Vote be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both. These things we apprehend to be utterly contrary to our Discipline, and Constitution of our Colloquies. <hi>Sirs,</hi> We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, Our Deputies should forthwith return to <hi>Norwich,</hi> by reason of the great expences We are at; and because there is no great hopes of doing any good, toward a Peace of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; by reason of the Irregularity: And also, because our antient Pastour, the Doctor <hi>De Laune,</hi> can no longer exercise the function of the Ministery, by reason of his great Age, and Weakness of Body: Nevertheless, It hath pleased God, that of late we have seen him, and heard him in the Pulpit, and in the Celebration of the Holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of Our LORD; to our great
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38165:45"/> Joy, and comfort, and peace: Which peace we wish unto you all, and rest, your Servants, who desire, and pray for peace among you all; Abiding yours, and in the Name of all.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Signed.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter de Laune,</hi> P.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Lange,</hi> Elders.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daniel Josse,</hi> Elders.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cornelius du Molin,</hi> Elders.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Castell,</hi> Deacons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philip Marlie,</hi> Deacons.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jos: Carpenter,</hi> Deacons.</item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We desire no alteration in the Holy Supper of the <hi>Lord,</hi> while our Churches are in trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Superscribed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To our honoured Brethren, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Ministers, and Elders, met in Colloquie, in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:38165:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To which last mentioned Petition, Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate, and Letter, his</hi> Highness <hi>was gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleased to return this Answer:</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>OLIVER P.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE having been appealed unto by divers Members of the French Church, residing in <hi>London,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning some supposed injury, done them by the Consistory; Which doth more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by a Petition preferred unto <hi>US,</hi> by the parties complaining: which <hi>WE</hi> have herewith sent you: Unto which the said Consistory have put in their Answer; And the Complainants have replyed: which papers also <hi>WE</hi> herewith send you: And perceiving, the taking the proofs, and stating the whole business, will ask more time, then <hi>WE</hi> can afford: And being willing, the said matters in question may be composed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to equity: <hi>WE</hi> have thought fit, and doe hereby referre the said business unto you, or any three, or more of you, to hear what both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have to say for the making good their matters: Who have promised <hi>US,</hi> to attend you therein: That so, when you shall have soe heard the same, you may report back
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:38165:46"/> unto <hi>US</hi> the state of the business; together with your opinion thereupon.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi>
                        <date>the last day of <hi>October, 1656.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>To</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Philip Nye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Will: Cooper.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Sam: Bamford.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>William Carter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Thom: M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Will: Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>ns.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Mr. <hi>Geo: Griffith.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Now for the further satisfaction of the Reader, We shall also give relation, of the Sense of the Consistory of the Church of</hi> Canterbury; <hi>As by an Extract of the Articles of the Walloon Consistory in</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury; <hi>of the</hi> 19<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. <hi>and</hi> 22<seg rend="sup">••</seg>. <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>1656. Translated out of French, appears; As followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="excerpt">
                        <p>The <hi>Company</hi> of the <hi>Walloon Consistory</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (with the Deacons,) having heard the Rehearsall of the things, past among the Deputies of our Churches, which met at <hi>London</hi> the <hi>22</hi> of <hi>August</hi> last, and the daies following; having also seen the Acts of the Consistory, and also of the <hi>Coetus</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> Unto which the approbation, and acquiescing of Mr <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey</hi> hath been required: And the offers that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38165:46"/> the said Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> hath made to the said Consistory, conteined in three propositions; having also seen the pretended Sentence of the pretended Colloquie, against the said Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> which was published in the Pulpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, one Lords day in the morning, by Mr. <hi>Stouppe;</hi> though it had not heen intimated before to the said Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi> and no advertisement was given unto him of the publishing thereof. These things maturely considered; And after the calling upon the Name of God, the <hi>Company</hi> judgeth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> Not to acknowledge, nor to be able to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that there hath been a lawful Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie, among the said Deputies; to iudge of the Differences of the Church of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> Because, (contrary to the Discipline of our Churches,) Mr. <hi>Du Perrier,</hi> was there ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as Pastour; Who never received the Imposition of hands, in the reformed Churches; And hath no oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r Ordination, but that of a Priest in the Romish Church.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> Because, having (after a deliberate Consideration of all things,) expressly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted our Deputies, as Judges of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of <hi>London;</hi> They have after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, (without cause,) taken away one of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38165:47"/> their Votes to please the Consistory of <hi>London,</hi> and to blemish our Church, by maiming it: For the which cause, we have commanded our Deputies to withdraw from such a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: Or not to sit, but with right to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, of such an unrighteousness to the next Colloquie.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> Because also, they were not a sufficient number to compose a Colloquie, to judge of matters of so great Importance: For, of seven Churches of our language in this Land, there were at the first, onely the Deputies of two Churches: <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>Southam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton;</hi> (whereof one was the aforesaid Mr. <hi>Du Perrier:</hi>) who have undertaken to judge, as having an authority of a Colloquie. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, their number was increased by one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Dover;</hi> (For the Elder was constrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to withdraw, by reason of the Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his <hi>Highness</hi> the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning those that have been in armes against the <hi>State.</hi>) They, at the Conclusion of their Assembly, have added to themselves, a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Person of the Church of <hi>Dover;</hi> who was then in <hi>London;</hi> but without Letters; and without the choice, and knowledge of the said Church: Which is altogether extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> Because, they have refused from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38165:47"/> of their meeting, to write to the Churches absent, to exhort them to come, according to the practice in such a Case: As appeareth by the Colloquie in the year, <hi>1647.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <hi>5.</hi> Finally, and most of all; because, when the Deputies of the other Churches were come, and there was a possibility to compose a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie, of all the Deputies of our Churches: And notice of it, being given unto them; they have the very next day with-drawn; flying, and shuning all Communion, and correspondence with their Brethren. Whence, it doth appear, that that company was notoriously factious, and did not seek the peace of the Churches: But onely to oppose one party, to please the other. For at least, they were to shew the other <hi>Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> what they had done, that they might have their advise.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> The said <hi>Company</hi> of the Consistory, (with the <hi>Deacons</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>) judgeth, and declareth; That Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> hath been unjust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interdicted, and without cause, by the French Consistory of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> Because a Consistory hath not that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, (according to our Discipline,) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdict a Pastour, for any cause whatsoever; without calling first, two or three Pastours,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38165:48"/> (not suspected;) which hath not been done by the Consistory of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> Because the non-acquiescence to those three Acts of the said Consistory, or of the <hi>Coetus,</hi> is no cause for the suspension of a Pastour; Who is of singular edification to the Church; and in whose life, and doctrine his greatest enemies have nothing to upbraid him with.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> Because Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> by his Offers, in three Propositions, satisfieth abundantly to the <hi>Discipline,</hi> and to all, what the Consistory might justly require of him in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> Because by the refusal of the proffers of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth occasion to think, that they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the Word of God, and the Discipline; and that they will establish themselves Judges above the word of God; and that they will not give the Liberty unto Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> to preach against all manner of Errors, and Vices, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out respect of persons; But that they will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> in his Conscience, and take away from him the Liberty, due to every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the Gospel.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, seeing the said Deputies have approved all the proceedings of the Consistory of <hi>London:</hi> And have appointed, (as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:38165:48"/> that their pretended Sentence should be publickly read in the Pulpit, (without being made known before hand to Mr. <hi>Delmey;</hi>) They have manifestly declared themselves partial, and unjust against our Discipline. And our most humble, and ardent desire is, that it would please his <hi>Highness</hi> the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> to take the cause in hand, and to deliver the oppressed, and all our Churches, from this Tyranny; according to the example of the good Christian Emperors; Wherein his <hi>Highness</hi> shall not prejudice our Discipline; But rather shall establish it against the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of those, who seek to overthrow it.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed by,
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>One Minister.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Eight Elders.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Eight Deacons.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>And further to justifie, and maintein the Opinion, and Judgement of the Officers in Consistory of the said Church in</hi> Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>and also of the Reverend</hi> English Divines,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38165:49"/>
               <hi>(hereafter declared,) We shall here insert some Acts of our Colloquies, antient, and modern, instead of many others which we might produce: Whereby we hope, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will evidently discern, That the Suspen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Mr.</hi> Delmey <hi>is altogether unjust, and unwarrantable; And that all the specious pretences of the Pamphlettors, are fictitious and delusory: And therefore we shall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Translation of those Acts, out of French, as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div n="10" type="colloquy">
                        <head>Colloquie the tenth.</head>
                        <p>The Articles of Colloquie of the French Churches, gathered in this Kingdome, held in <hi>Norwich,</hi> the 25<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. of <hi>April,</hi> and other daies following▪ in the year of our <hi>Lord, 1593.</hi> In which, (after the Invocation of the Name of God,) Mr. <hi>Lescailiet</hi> was chosen to moderate the Action, and <hi>Phillip de la Motte,</hi> for Scribe.</p>
                        <div n="1" type="article">
                           <head>Article the first.</head>
                           <p>Upon the Appeal of the Brother Mr. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Bayard,</hi> and his rejecting of the Sentence of the Consistory of the Church of <hi>Norwich,</hi> for his Suspension from the holy Sacrament; and appearing before the Colloquie: All things having been seriously examined on all sides,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:38165:49"/> the final Sentence was pronounced unto the said Brother <hi>Bayard,</hi> and unto the Consistory of the said Church. That on the one side, the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bayard</hi> had not a sufficient Foundation, upon which he could build an assured right up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church of <hi>Norwich;</hi> and that he had greatly forgotten himself in his Outrages, with many Defamations against all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in a publick Sermon, to the Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of good people; Notwitstanding the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his pretended Right: And is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to desist in his demand, and confess his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving offended God, and the Church. On the other side, that the Consistory, (having sent the Judgment to the people; An action doubtful! without endeavouring a Friendly Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the said <hi>Bayard</hi> to give him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: And it being too much to precipitate, to give Sentence of Suspension against a Minister of the Word, without calling some other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stours of other Churches, and to call him, or them more than one time to their company;) shall be admonished to take off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>he said Suspension; So as <hi>Bayard</hi> confesseth his fault; They giving him some reasonable recompence, in considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he was mistaken, and overtaken by those, that were in charge in the Church, seven years since, for to hold him tyed, and in Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, without giving him any assurance of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38165:50"/> Obligation. To this Judgement all have acquiesced so well, that the above said suspension was taken off; And being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, have given hands one to the other, in witnesse of their mutuall brotherly union. The Papers, and Acts of this difference, and many dependances more, amply set forth, have been delivered into the hands of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Hampton,</hi> by the advise of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the said Colloquie.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="act">
                           <head>The second Act of the said Colloquie.</head>
                           <p>If a Minister be convicted of Enormous, and notorious crimes, He shall be suddenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the Consistory, (they having called two, or three Pastors, not suspested.) And in case, that the Delinquent complain of the witnesses, or of Calumnie: The fact shall be reported to the Colloquie: And if he hath preached, or taught hereticall Doctrines, he shall suddenly be suspended by the Consistory; (two, or three Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters being called, as above;) untill that the Colloquie hath ended the same. As for the cause of his deposition, that shall not be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the people; If the necessity doe not require it: Of which the Consistory shall judge.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27" type="colloquy">
                        <pb n="87" facs="tcp:38165:50"/>
                        <head>Colloquie 27. in the year, 1646. Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in <hi>London.</hi> Friday 31. <hi>July,</hi> Article 65.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Upon the question, what formality is to be observed by a Church, which doth pretend to have something to object against its Pastour, in regard of Doctrine, or in regard of carriage: It hath been answered in such Case; If the Consistory cannot have assistance of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-Pastours, They shall give advise of their griefs to the Sister-Churches, for to proceed the more safe, untill a final decision by the Colloquie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And now we doubt not, but these Acts, and Resolutions of our Colloquies, will fully satisfie the judicious Reader; And for the truth thereof, We appeal to all the French Churches in <hi>England,</hi> whither they are not in force, and unrepealed: And as we are informed, the Dutch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory in <hi>London,</hi> (assisted with other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of some other of the Dutch-Churches,) have very lately proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the same manner, in a Difference
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38165:51"/> depending in the Dutch Church in <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi> And therefore, as to the French Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory of <hi>London</hi>'s Actions against Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> We shall leave them to be compared, and commensurated, by the Scale, and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Readers Impartiall Judgement.</p>
            <p>Upon which Reference of his <hi>Highness</hi> to the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id <hi>Divines</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; They fully heard both parties, and all their Allegations, and proofs; And as to their Judgements, and Opinions concerning the said <hi>Colloquie,</hi> They reported to his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> their Sense, in or about 19. <hi>June,</hi> 1657. (after a long time in attending the <hi>Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>'s producing their Papers, and making their Defence,) in this manner: <hi>That they did humbly certifie; That as to the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the late</hi> Colloquie, <hi>(called by his</hi> High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness <hi>Order,) upon the Petition of the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families <hi>and complained of by the said</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families, <hi>in their papers to his</hi> Highness; <hi>That according to the Discipline of the said Churches, a</hi> Colloquie <hi>is to consist of all the French Churches in this Nation: a Minister, and an Elder from every Church. And they found by the book of</hi> Colloquies, <hi>that in seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty sixe years, the Churches have called twenty nine</hi> Colloquies: <hi>In seven of which the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of all the Churches, (except one,) appeared;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38165:51"/> And the absent Churches questioned, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured; Though it is said, the absence was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned, partly by the Bishop of</hi> Norwich; <hi>and partly by reason, that two successive Ministers in</hi> Hampton, <hi>were much, and long afflicted with the Gout, and so could not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel: In three other Colloquies, the Deputies of all the Churches met, (except one Elder,) for which the Church was censured: And in all the other nineteen Colloquies, all the Deputies of all the French Churches were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent: But in this last Colloquie, (though there be seven Churches of the French Nation in</hi> England,) <hi>the Referrees found but five Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in all, (besides the Deputies of the Church in</hi> London, <hi>which were the Parties complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of,) that is to say, from</hi> Norwich <hi>two, from</hi> Hampton <hi>two, and from</hi> Dover <hi>one: For the Elder from</hi> Dover, <hi>having been a Delinquent in Arms, left the Citty within a day, or two after he came, upon his</hi> Highness <hi>Proclamation: The Deputies of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>(having sate in the beginning of the Colloquie; And having one of their Votes injuriously taken from them; And an Order being made, that they should have but one Vote between them,) with-drew from the Assembly, before the Deputies of</hi> Dover <hi>came to Town; And were not afterwards admitted to sit in Colloquie:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38165:52"/> And the Deputies of</hi> Santhoff, <hi>and</hi> Thorney Abbey <hi>not comeing in time, sate not at all; The Colloquie first refusing to write to them to come, as hath been used in former Colloquies, (though they were desired so to doe by the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families;) <hi>And then at last dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solving themselves in hast, just that night, that those Deputies came to Town. On all which proceedings the Deputies of</hi> London, <hi>(who are parties) are thought to have a great Influence; Mr.</hi> Cisner, <hi>(the man most com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of,) being for the most part present in, and Moderator of the Assemhly: And of those five persons that sate, two of them, to wit, the Deputies of the Church of</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich <hi>were sent for home by their Consistory; who disapproved of the Acts of that Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie, as being contrary to their Discipline, and the constitution of their Colloquies. And the Minister of</hi> Hampton, <hi>having been a Priest in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and not since Ordeined in any Reformed Church, (For ought appears in their Papers,) was not capable by their Discipline to sit in Colloquie. Notwithstanding which, that Colloquie took upon them, to make Acts in Confirmation of the aforesaid Acts of the Consistory in</hi> London, <hi>to censure the</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>of</hi> Families, <hi>for submitting to His</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:38165:52"/> Highness<hi>'s Proposition of referring their Differences to</hi> English Ministers; <hi>And to admit of the Observation of</hi> Holy daies, <hi>contrary to former Acts of</hi> Colloquie, &amp;c. <hi>So as the</hi> Referrees <hi>unanimously did conceive, that that</hi> Colloquie <hi>was neither rightly constituted, nor did regularly act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reader may also take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> was President, for the most part, of that pretended Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, (Being the party most complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned against:) And albeit, that he is not yet rightfully ordeined, according to our Discipline; (As he hath lately confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed:) In like manner as the Minister of <hi>Southampton</hi> is not, (who hath been a Romish Priest.) And also, being desired by the Deputies, and <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> (upon the first Assembling of those Deputies,) that a Fast might be kept for humiliation of the Church; Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> uncharitably answered, <hi>That Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, (when they had any wickednesse
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38165:53"/> to Act,) would keep a Fast:</hi> And the Dutch also, by two of their Elders, requested the same; Offering for that purpose, to keep a Fast the same day in their Church: But the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> refused, contrary to severall Acts of our Colloquies, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experiences, and common practices.</p>
            <p>Upon the consideration of which last men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Petition, Certificate,</hi> and other <hi>Proofs,</hi> and the <hi>Reference</hi> from, and <hi>Report</hi> to his <hi>Highness;</hi> Whereby not onely his <hi>Highness</hi> did declare his Judgment: But the said seven <hi>English Divines,</hi> did unanimously agree, that upon matter of fact, aswell as right, the said Colloquie was not rightly constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor did regularly act; It will be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorie, and sufficient enough, That the said <hi>Consistory,</hi> and all their proceedings have been arbitrary, and usurped: And that Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> have been wrongfully abused, and injured: And that they ought to be justly vindicated, aswell in respect of themselves, as the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Discipline of all the Churches: So that Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> may no longer be obstruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Exercise of his Charge: But have liberty to preach in that Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impediment, or any violence offered to him: And the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> (who
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38165:53"/> have been wrongfully suspended,) may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his Ministery in all the parts thereof, with all such as will walk regularly, and according to the Word of God, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline: For that, (as by the said last reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Petition appears,) Aswell the sixe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, (being Ministers, and Elders,) who were elected, and sent for Deputies to the said Assembly; as also the Consistories of the Churches in <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> have, (as aforesaid,) disapproved, and disown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Actions, (as irregular,) of the other five persons, as to their Constitution of a Colloquie; as also the Proceedings of the Consistory of London, as being contrary to the Discipline of all the French Churches in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And furthermore, whereas in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion of the said Appendix to that Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet, the <hi>Authors</hi> alleadge, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey <hi>hath rejected their Acts of Colloquie; as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as he had slighted those of the Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of the Coetus; pretending many things to justifie his denyall of submission to them; Whose objections they had fully refuted; yet offering, If he find himself grieved by the Sentence of the Colloquie, (though he might be no more received to any Appeal, having slipped his time,) He shall have nevertheless
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38165:54"/> liberty to appeal to a</hi> Synod, <hi>assembled of the</hi> Dutch, <hi>and</hi> French <hi>Churches in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: <hi>Which he yet slights; Requiring to be judged by</hi> English Ministers: <hi>Whereto the Authours pretend they cannot consent,</hi> &amp;c. To this We answer, That for the Reasons, and Relations before mentioned, Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> cannot be thought, (without manifest wrong to his Conscience, and Infringing the Discipline, and Government of all the said French Churches,) to admit the said Assemblie to be a Colloquie, rightly constituted, and compounded; Nor can it be fairly objected against him, that he hath any waies slighted the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistories Acts; otherwise, then by making a Just Appeal, to a lawfull Judicatorie from them; As by right he may, and ought to doe: And for the Acts of the Coetus, they are insignificant, and not obliging: In as much, as the Dutch Consistory disclaime any power over the French, either as joined with, or divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from them; Further then by a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary submission, and Consent of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Nor have they any more, or greater power, then English Ministers may have by such Condescension, and Agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yet nevertheless the Pamphlettors
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38165:54"/> are so confident, (without any respect to their Brethren; Over whom they neither can, nor ought to be Superiours, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violating their Bond of Love, and Union,) to propose to Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> (As if they had some speciall power in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves above all the rest of our Churches,) <hi>That he shall have liberty to appeal to a</hi> Synod <hi>of the</hi> Dutch, <hi>and</hi> French Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Whereas it cannot be denyed, But that the Dutch of <hi>London,</hi> are by profession, more enclined to the Actions of the Consistory, and have been much Contributory to them, by certifiing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in their behalfe, (As the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plettors suggest,) for their advantage: And so in common equity, it cannot be demanded, That Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> should sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to such Judges; If there were nothing to be pleaded by him for the antient Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline, and Government of the French Churches apart, and distinctly by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. And for the Pamphlettors not submitting to English Ministers, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry disingenuously insisted upon; Since that it is not without Precedent, that, (in Mr. <hi>Cisners</hi> own Case formerly,) Some Scotch, aswell as English Ministers interposed to accommodate some differences occasioned by him. And
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38165:55"/> moreover, (as by his <hi>Highness</hi> last Order of Reference, and other proofs, apppears;) the Consistory submitted willingly to his <hi>Highness</hi> said Referrees. Wherefore, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the Pamphlettors great pretences, for the said Assemblies great care in making their pretended Acts, according to common Discipline, and Colloquies, and Consisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Acts; Whereby they would vainly justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, against palpaple Evidence of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, their obstinate, and unwarrantable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment towards Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and the said <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families:</hi> Yet let the Reader courteously dijudicate, and distinguish upon all the Premisses; And we doubt not, but that the Innocence, and Justice of our Cause will be defended, and propugned by his judicious, and impartiall Censure. And that the Consistorie, or their Abettors, can in no wise fairly, and candidly answer, or positively deny these following <hi>Quaeres,</hi> which we, according to the constitutions of our Discipline, and Church Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Acts of Colloquies, (not desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to invade, or incroach upon the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of any other persons, but to avouch, and maintein our own,) do offer, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to publick Consideration, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:38165:55"/>1. <hi>Whither a Consistory of any of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ought to oppose the Assembling of a Colloquie, or Petition against it, according to the Discipline of our Churches in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whither a Caetus hath power to judge, after an Appeal made to a Colloquie, without consent of parties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whither five persons can be a Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie for sixe Churches, when some of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties are also incapable to sit in Colloquie; And others that are capable kept out; And the said five persons refused to write to the Churches absent: And when their proceedings are disavowed by one Consistory, which sent two of those five persons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whither a Caetus, or Synod with the</hi> Dutch, <hi>be any part of the</hi> French <hi>Discipline? And whither the French have any power, (in Church Government,) over the</hi> Dutch; <hi>or the</hi> Dutch <hi>over the</hi> French?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Whither a Consistory of themselves, have power to set up Holy Daies, After that they are abolished by several Colloquies of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:38165:56"/>6. <hi>Whither a Consistory of themselves; can cast out a Minister for any Cause whatever: And especially after he hath appealed to a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie by their Consent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Whither a Consistory can suspend from the</hi> Lords Supper, <hi>severall Members of their</hi> Church, <hi>for petitioning to the chief Magistrate to preserve their Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8, <hi>Whither a Consistory can put several Deacons out of the Consistory, because they would not retract their Appeal made to a Colloquie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Whither five persons assembled, under the pretended form of a Colloquie, can censure any Member for obeying the chief Magistrate of the Nation: When what is done, is for to preserve the Government, and peace of the Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Whither such five persons (so assembled,) can confirm all the aforesaid proceedings,</hi> viz. <hi>concerning the Observation of Holy daies, the ejection of Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>the suspension of seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Members from the</hi> Lords Supper, <hi>the putting of the Deacons out of the Consistory, and all the Irregularities before mentioned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:38165:56"/>
            <p>These several Quaeres being duely consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; It cannot be disproved (we hope,) but that they comprehend, and contein the whole State, and Substance of all the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in dispute between us in the said <hi>French Churches.</hi> And if by a sober, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Reply thereto, we can be convinced, and confuted, that We are in an Errour, and not justly defended by our Discipline, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Acts of our Colloquies: We shall willingly embrace those opprobrious Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of being factious Rebells against Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Orders, and to be accompted disturbers, and breakers of the peace of the Churches, (as the Pamphlettors doe term us.) And hereby promise to submit to any Censures, that shall be for that cause, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed on us by a Colloquie of all the <hi>French Churches,</hi> legally and rightly to be convened, and assembled, according to our Discipline and Customes. And if by their Judgement We shall be acquitted and justified, We fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope, all Godly, and good men, will esteem it equitable, and conformable to common Justice, That the innocent should not be condemned with the guilty. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the peace, and quiet of our Churches, his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> by and with the advice and consent of his Right-honourable privie Councill, do gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38165:57"/> interpose to redress our grievances, We shall account his <hi>Highness</hi>'s justice to be most acceptable to us, &amp; no waies infringing the order of our Discipline and Government. Which submission of ours, We humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will satisfie the Christian Reader, how much we desire the Peace, and Order of our Churches; And that if the Opponents can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not convince us, This <hi>Refutation</hi> of their Pamphlet shall stand for a full and sufficient Vindication of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and all others concerned in our Differences, without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Addition, or Supplement.</p>
            <p>But by way of <hi>Corollary,</hi> We shall earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly request the <hi>Candid Reader</hi> to consider, with what <hi>malignity,</hi> and <hi>virulence</hi> of Spirit the said Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> (with some of the <hi>London</hi> Consistory,) are infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Who, together with Mr. <hi>Payen,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stour, (one of the five persons, assembled in <hi>London,</hi> before-mentioned,) and some of the Consistory of <hi>Dover,</hi> have since the Session of those five persons, in the pretended Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie, in <hi>August,</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> 1656. par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly attempted to confound the Peace, and Government of that ancient well order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Walloon-Congregation</hi> in <hi>Canterbury:</hi> And
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:38165:57"/> to that end have advised, and encouraged particular Members thereof, who (being some of them debauched, and scandalous,) have been suspended from the Lords Supper almost ten or eleven years, by Letters, and otherwise; Approveing their gathering of hands, and sending to <hi>France</hi> for Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> (a Minister,) who upon that call came to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and there, (though desired,) he refused to treat with the Consistory of that Church: And the Lords day following, (contrary to the consent of the <hi>Major</hi> of that Citty,) preached in the morning in one of the English Churches: and in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, (without any mature deliberation,) elected Elders, and Deacons, (altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to him for their conversations;) which was such a rash, and inconsiderate Action, as it doth not onely manifest the animosity of the Confederates, but is an absolute Rupture and breach of the good Government of that Church, and all other the <hi>French Churches</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the <hi>Walloon</hi> Consistory in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> sent by Letter to advise with the <hi>London</hi> Consistory: Who refused to answer their Letter, (though entreated by an Elder of their own;) yet nevertheless Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Paul D'Obey</hi> (an Elder,) and others
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:38165:58"/> of that Consistory, wrote to those new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious persons, animating, and exhorting them to expedite their proceedings; for that in short time, their new Church (so schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically erected,) should be acknowledged the Regular Church, and as regular, as their Church in <hi>London;</hi> as some of those disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly persons themselves have related in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> After which counsell, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, they have hitherto made their progress: and Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> hath setled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and his family there, making a Voiage to <hi>France</hi> to bring them over. In whose ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence Mr. <hi>Payen</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> and the malignant Elder before mentioned, who left <hi>London</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Highness</hi> Proclamation, came to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury:</hi> And on a Lords day Mr. <hi>Payen</hi> preached, and administred the Lords Supper to this upstart, disorderly Congregation. And Mr. <hi>Jannôn,</hi> (at his return from <hi>France,</hi>) preached at <hi>Dover</hi> to Mr. <hi>Payen</hi>'s Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and afterwards when he arrived again at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> an Elder now in Consistory of the French Church in <hi>London,</hi> being then at <hi>Canterbury</hi> with his wife, did publickly own the said Mr. <hi>Jannôn,</hi> and his irregular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. All which actions are directly opposite, and contrary to the express words of an act of Colloquie made in the year, 1646. hereafter specified.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:38165:58"/>
            <p>Which combination doth evidently dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Consistory in <hi>London,</hi> in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to corroborate and strengthen their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: whereby not onely to propagate such disorders, and infringe the Government of all the French Churches in <hi>England;</hi> But also to eject Mr. <hi>Philip le Keux,</hi> (a godly and faithfull Pastour in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as there it hath been reported;) As they have unjust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done by Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi> in <hi>London:</hi> For Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> hath uttered in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (as others have also said in <hi>London,) That it will not be well with the Strangers-Churches, till their English Ministers are expulsed; meaning Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>and Mr.</hi> le Keux, <hi>being born in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>These unhappy, and irregular Actions falling out, the <hi>Walloon</hi> Consistory in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> (depending their differences,) did write to the Synod of the French Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in <hi>Holland,</hi> assembled at <hi>Roterdam</hi> in <hi>September</hi> last past, complaining of the great Rent made in that Church by disorderly people, and praying that grave Assembly to recommend a Godly Minister to officiate therein.</p>
            <p>Whereupon that grave Assembly took their sad condition into serious considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And by their Letters returned, <hi>did not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:38165:59"/> onely bewail the Breach in that Church, but also depute Mr.</hi> Stuart <hi>Minister, to make a voyage to</hi> Canterbury, <hi>to be Assistant to Mr.</hi> Phillip le Keux, <hi>Pastour in that Church, till they should otherwise provide for themselves; Professing that they were thereunto obliged by the communion of Saints.</hi> And also the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Moderator, <hi>Monsieur De la Riviere,</hi> (who signed that Letter in the name of the Synod,) commiserating the Condition of that Church, <hi>which he termed antient, and composed of the best party of the</hi> Walloons <hi>in</hi> Canterbury, declared in that Synod, <hi>that if he were able to travell, he would willi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gly cross the Seas to endeavour the good of that Church:</hi> Whose Christian expressions so far prevailed, That divers Ministers volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily profered their service, even to absent themselves from their Families for some time, to assist that Church, if the Synod would depute them. Upon which Mr. <hi>Stuart</hi> being elected by the <hi>major</hi> part of the Synod was ordered to be sent over lately for that service of Love, and is expected accordingly.</p>
            <p>This Relation is here inserted, that the Reader may the better understand, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their party doe demean themselves; And whither their comportment be in that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38165:59"/> Christian-like manner, and corresponding with that pious, and reverend Assemblie's in <hi>Holland;</hi> who vouchsafed spontaneously, and freely their compassionate Letter, and assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance; Albeit they were not under the the same Obligations of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: When as, Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and others of their party, refused to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the said <hi>Walloon</hi> Consistorie's Letter; and under hand, and indirectly some of them incited and instigated Mr. <hi>Jannôn,</hi> and his scandalous, and schismaticall Faction; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by our Discipline, and Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they were engaged, (for all the Churches unity, and peace,) to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>Wherefore considering all the evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of the premisses; and withall that all our French Churches were likely to be destroyed; The Consistory in <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> have unanimously Petitioned his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> (no other means being left them;) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming him of the premisses, and their sad condition, occasioned by Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and some of the <hi>London</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory. And for proof thereof they have annexed a Certificate from the <hi>Major</hi> of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> certifying his dislike of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious proceedings of the said disorderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:38165:60"/> with some particulars thereof; and also an <hi>Affidavit</hi> of four credible persons made before him. Which Petition, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers remain before his <hi>Highness,</hi> and his Council; From whom, that Consistory humbly pray, and wait for relief.</p>
            <p>Moreover, (since that Occurrences doe daily, most sadly evene,) We shall further enarrate, and declare to the Reader, whose too much tired patience We crave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect with candour, and benevolence; That Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> with some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their adherents, assiduously, and diligently persist in their Machinations, and unworthy complotting against the said <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loon</hi> Church in <hi>Canterbury:</hi> In as much as on the 5 <hi>October</hi> last, Mr. <hi>Payen,</hi> Minister in <hi>Dover,</hi> (one of the five persons sitting in the said pretended Colloquie, before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained against; together with his before-mentioned malignant Elder,) came then to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and had much private discourse with Mr. <hi>Jannôn,</hi> and several members of his schismaticall Faction, and the next day returned to <hi>Dover:</hi> But the day after that, Mr. <hi>Payen</hi> came again to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and with Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> immedietely set forward for <hi>London,</hi> (it being then given out in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> should preach
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:38165:60"/> in the French Church in <hi>London,</hi> and be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the <hi>Coetus;</hi> Where the next day being <hi>Thursday,</hi> they arrived; On which very night, a Consistory of the French Church in <hi>London,</hi> was called to meet the next morning early, who met accordingly; and, (as some of them have reported,) the occasion was to order, that Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi> might preach in that Church the Lords day following in the morning; Which was by them debated, and Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> went to Mr. <hi>Jannôn</hi>'s lodging, (being neer to Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s house,) desiring him to preach; Who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised so to doe, and was expected accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly by many people, who went purposely to hear him: But by the indisposition of his health, (as it is said,) he sent the Man of the house where he lodged, to Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> intreating an excuse.</p>
            <p>By which passage, (although perhaps by some it may be lightly accounted,) yet the Reader we hope will be convinced, that Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> with their correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents doe still animate, and abett Mr. <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nôn</hi> and his irregular upstart faction, to the great disquiet and distraction of the said <hi>Walloon</hi> Church in <hi>Canterbury;</hi> and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly design also the trouble and perplexity of the Church in <hi>London;</hi> So as, (if they
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:38165:61"/> could,) they would by their evill practices, and Confederacies utterly eradicate, and subvert the whole Government of all the French Churches in <hi>England:</hi> Howsoever they pretend, (but meerly by Collusion,) their assiduity, and care to maintein the Discipline thereof. Which will be more clearly discovered, and unveiled; If the Reader be pleased to consider the 105. Article, Entred, Thursday the third of <hi>September,</hi> 1646. of the twenty seventh Colloquie assembled in <hi>London</hi> in May preceding; translated out of French, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For prevention of Schismes, and many other disorders which do slide into our Churches, The</hi> Company <hi>doth declare; that if there be any Minister, either amongst Us, or without, that doth establish Assemblies apart there, where a Church is already constituted; because it doth overthrow the maintenance of the holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, and the relief of the Poor, and openeth the door to all sorts of Sects, and Opinions: They are Infringers of the Discipline, and Disturbers of the rest of the Churches. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if such an one be amongst Us, he is sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a Censure, untill a Deposition. If he be from without, he is lyable to be deposed,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:38165:61"/> and unworthy of the holy Ministery: And the principall Authors, and Fomentors of such irregular Assemblies shall be dealt withall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rigour of the Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the severity of this Article be not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positively, and directly against the Interpella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Interfaring of Mr. <hi>Jannôn,</hi> in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to establish a new Assembly at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury;</hi> whereby himfelf, and his Fomentours are subject to the rigour and censures of our Discipline; let the Reader be pleased im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially to define, and adjudge.</p>
            <p>And now to return to the proper business of our selves; And thereby, (as far as we can,) to manifest, and illustrate the truth, and our Innocence, with our ardent desires of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all satisfaction, and peace: We held it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to address our selves to the Consistory of the Dutch by Letter: Whereby we desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to give us Christian satisfaction, As by the matter it self to them proposed in the words following, will evidently appear, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:38165:62"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honoured Brethren in Consistorie.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu may be pleased to remember, That the <hi>13</hi> of this instant month, Seven <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> of the French Church <hi>London,</hi> for themselves, and others, appeared at your Church before your Consistory, and presented a Paper: A Copy whereof, (as was desired,) was delivered the next day to Mr. <hi>Nicholas Corsellis;</hi> And conteined, as followeth.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> If a <hi>Coetus</hi> of the Stangers-Churches in <hi>London,</hi> have any power over any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, or member thereof, or any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference therein; after an Appeal made to a Colloquie of their own Churches? And if any such practice hath been since the constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Colloquies.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> If such power in a <hi>Coetus</hi> be pretended! If then the <hi>Dutch</hi> have any power over the <hi>French,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> over the <hi>Dutch,</hi> by the Discipline, or Acts of Colloquies of either Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:38165:62"/>
                     <hi>3.</hi> If the Colloquies of the Churches of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Language have heretofore ordered, That an Appeal may be made from either Colloquie to a Synod of both Nations? And if such an Appeal be approved of by the Discipline of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches? And what Directions, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities are there prescribed for the making of such an Appeal?</p>
                  <p>Which being presented, our Members with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew: And after a long debate by your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, They were called in. And Mr. <hi>Calan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drain,</hi> your Moderator, was pleased to answer our two first Quaeres, Negatively; That the <hi>Dutch</hi> had no power over the <hi>French,</hi> nor the <hi>French</hi> over the <hi>Dutch:</hi> And the third he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered affirmatively: That Synods of both Colloquies had power: But could not declare the formality, how it should be constituted; Or when Synods atteined that power, And in fine gave no satisfactory Answer, concerning the Discipline of either Church: concluding that we should propose that question to the <hi>Coetus:</hi> Because the Certificate, in dispute, was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the <hi>Coetus</hi> to the French Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:38165:63"/>
                  <p>Hereupon the twentieth of this Moneth, we attended the <hi>Coetus,</hi> and proposed that third Question unto them: To which Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> (their Moderatour,) replyed; <hi>That we ought to have addressed to the</hi> French <hi>Consistory first; and our appearing there was irregular: And therefore the</hi> Coetus <hi>could give no other answer.</hi> Which to Us seemed very strange: Since we pursued Your own direction: And the matter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly concerned not the <hi>French,</hi> but your selves, and the <hi>Italian Church:</hi> And we professed, That if a <hi>Synod</hi> had any such power; (of which we desired Information,) We should render Obedience thereto; Not yet knowing, that they had any such faculty, or power. We also prayed the <hi>Coetus</hi> to vouchsafe Us a Coppy of the <hi>Certificate</hi> signed by some of your selves, and others of the <hi>Italian Church;</hi> Which was delivered to the <hi>French</hi> Consistory: Whereto Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi> replyed, <hi>That it was not the Custome of the</hi> Coetus <hi>to give Copies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By which equivocall Answer, We have not Justice done Us, either for matter, or manner; For, (as to the matter,) You ought to have clearly answered our last Question, as well as the two others; For
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:38165:63"/> that, You with the <hi>Italian Church</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a Certificate, to the purpose mentioned in the <hi>Petition</hi> of the French Consistory to his <hi>Highness</hi> the <hi>Lord Protector.</hi> And for the manner, You have permitted Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and others to Vote in their own Cause; Which is contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and common reason. Wherefore We again humbly request You to do Us right, by answering our said third Question, and justifiing your <hi>Certificate:</hi> Or else, We shall conclude, that You cannot in Justice defend it: Which we have good cause to beleeve You cannot do; Because Mr. <hi>Host,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Corsellis,</hi> (two eminent Members of Your Consistory,) have denyed the same: And in your Answeres to Our two former Questions, You have disproved a part of that <hi>Certificate.</hi> And as You are <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters,</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> appointed to rule ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Discipline, We intreat You to give Us Christian Satisfaction in Our desire: Otherwise You will give Us mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest occasion to suspect, that some of Your Consistory, have been instrumentall to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and chearish the troubles of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Which for our Vindication, We shall be necessarily engaged to publish to the <hi>World,</hi> (but with much grief, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:38165:64"/> remorse;) In case you shall not answer our just, and requisite Proposall: For which we wait, and attend your result, Remaining</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Christian Brethren, and Friends, in all the Bonds of Amitie, and love. Signed by,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Jurin</hi> Senior.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Daniel Fervacques.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Isaac Le Gay.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Peter Jurin.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:38165:64"/>
            <p>The twenty fourth day of <hi>September</hi> last, the four Subscribers of this Letter, attended the Dutch Consistory, and delivered it to Mr. <hi>Van Cewlen,</hi> (one of the Elders;) who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it into that Consistory; And after some attendance, returned them their Answer, <hi>That they understood they desired an Answer to the third Question, Therefore they must apply themselves to the Coetus.</hi> Which was all the answer they could get to the said Letter. Whereby the Reader may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised; whither the Dutch Consistory do not apparently reveal themselves to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and Fautors of our Differences: And were Agents in the Design of the French Consistory to subvert our Government; By insisting to promote, and erect a <hi>Coetus,</hi> or Synod of both Nations to be our judge, contrary to our antient and fundamentall Discipline. Yet however the seventh day of October also last past, two of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Subscribers of that Letter, did in a private and affectionate manner, desire Mr. <hi>William Cross,</hi> (one of the Elders of the Dutch Church,) that he would be pleased to propound to their Consistory once more, that satisfaction might yet be rendered to the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> of the French Church: So far forth, that if by any Rules, or dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:38165:65"/> (extant with them,) any power be rightfully invested in the Synod by the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the French Churches, (in the said Letter mentioned,) to order, or enact any finall Sentence in the matters before by us remonstrated; We should then upon full Evidence, and Demonstration thereof, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly acquiesce, and yield due obedience thereunto. But thereunto we could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein no more Satisfaction, then when the said Letter was presented to the Dutch Consistory.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to leave them without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, or pretence of Evasion, the said four Subscribers on Wednesday 14 <hi>October</hi> last, (being an ordinary Consistory day,) addressed again to the French Consistory; Informing, <hi>That they had atended the</hi> Coetus, <hi>for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the said third Question, concerning an Appeal to a Synod of both Nations, and the Formality of such Appeal:</hi> Whose answer was, <hi>That the appearing of the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies <hi>was irregular:</hi> But wherein we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand not! However those Subscribers <hi>were come to them for their answer thereunto;</hi> Desiring them, (if they could,) to maintein and prove, <hi>That there ought to be a Synod, either by the Discipline of the French Churches, or by some Act of Colloquie: And if so, we
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:38165:65"/> should render obedience thereto:</hi> After which they withdrew, and soon after were called in; and for answer that Consistory said, <hi>That they had other business before them, and therefore could give no Answer till eight daies were past.</hi> Whereto the Subscribers replyed, <hi>that if they intended to return Us to a</hi> Coetus, <hi>It might be done the next day, being the usuall day for the Dutch Consistorie's meeting; Intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to abridge their time, and give us their Answer in four daies; For that some of the Dutch Elders had already affirmed, That a Synod of both Nations had no power, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of parties.</hi> VVherefore after a second withdrawing, that Consistory <hi>would appoint no other time; nor gave they Us any direction fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to attend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding, being desirous to have satisfaction to the said third Question, the said four Subscribers of the aforesaid Letter, at the eight daies end, being the 21. of the said Moneth of <hi>October</hi> last past, attended again upon the Consistory of our Church: who being admitted to their presence, Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> (their Moderatour,) entred into a long discourse; Declaring to them, (amongst other things,) <hi>that in the year,</hi> 1593. <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made of a Synod; And that since that time, there had been</hi> 5. <hi>or</hi> 6. <hi>Synods; whose for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:38165:66"/> of convention was, by the Assembling of the Colloquies of both</hi> French, <hi>and</hi> Dutch <hi>Churches, together at one and the same time: And thereupon exhorted those Subscribers to submit thereto.</hi> Unto which the Subscribers replyed, that they came not thither to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in that particular; for that they well knew, there had been Synods: And they well approved either a Synod, or <hi>Coetus,</hi> in their proper nature, and order, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ends, for which they were intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Discipline of our French Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: hoping that the Consistorie would not deem them to be persons, that opposed them contrary to their usage in our Churches. But Mr. <hi>Cisner</hi>'s allegations were short in answering our Question: Which was, <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any publick, or private person, who had been censured by a Colloquie of our Churches, had power or permission to appeal to a</hi> Synod <hi>of both Nations? And if so, Then by what Examples positively to be produced by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory it could be manifested, when it was so done, and with what formality?</hi> And so the Subscribers desired a Copy of such their Testimonies, or Precedents. Whereupon Mr, <hi>Cisner</hi> (finding, that he could not make out any such thing to satisfie the four Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers,) did at length plainly confess, <hi>That
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:38165:66"/> the Appeals to such a Synod were left at liberty.</hi> Albeit the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Consistories, would averr it to be part of the Discipline, as by the Petition of the <hi>French</hi> Consistory to his <hi>Highness,</hi> appeareth. Wherefore the Subscribers desired them again to produce their Testimonies and Precedents. Which they said, they had, as also others unanswera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; to be made known in due time. And would give no further Answer, or satisfaction. Therefore the Subscribers proposed, that the Consistory would appoint two or three of themselves, to meet with the like number of the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> whereby mutual sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction might be given in a fair Discourse, and Treaty; And that, as they were a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, and Governours of the Church, and obliged to seek the peace thereof, they would procure a right understanding of the Point in Question. Whereupon, (Being first with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and the Consistory falling into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of that proposition,) the Subscribers were answered by two of their Members, (sent out on purpose,) That their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny had no more to say to them; Thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating their aversion, and backwardness to treat; or communicate upon any other sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and so dismissed them in that manner, as if they intended to have no more conference at all with them.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:38165:67"/>
            <p>These mediations, and transactions being had by Us, We intreat the Reader to consider, what equivocations, and Sophismes have been used to us, in being transferred from one to another: That when we desire satisfaction to 3 Questions, the Dutch Consistory by their own power answer to two of them; And as to the third direct us to the <hi>Coetus.</hi> And when we come to the <hi>Coetus,</hi> (consisting of Dutch French, and Italians;) then they decline, and say, (in generall termes onely,) our coming is Irregular. After this we address to the French Consistory; And they take upon them, (without a <hi>Coetus,</hi>) to answer us, but deferr it to another time; And then they give no satisfactory Answer at all, nor produce their Testimonies, nor accept of any propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, whereby mutuall Satisfaction might be rendred. And now; whither we have not done our duty, we appeal to all indifferent, and unbyassed Censures. But we shall palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and demonstratively refute, and reprove that assertion in the French Consistorie's Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, grounded upon the Certificate of the <hi>Coetus;</hi> If we first suppose, that the manner or formality of appealing to a Synod of both Nations, must of necessity be known to some persons or other. And for our parts we averr, that we never heard, that any one being
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:38165:67"/> censured by a Consistory, or Colloquie of the French Churches, had any power, or was permitted to appeal to a Synod of both Nations, or that any such practice was ever amongst us. But secondly, we shall prove the contrary by Precedent, and Acts of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies, made by all the Deputies of the French Churches in <hi>England.</hi> Especially (to instance in one, amongst many others which we can produce,) We shall vouch, the seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Article of the twenty sixt Colloquie, assembled in <hi>London,</hi> in the year, 1644. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears, <hi>That Mr.</hi> De Laune, <hi>Minister in Norwich, had a difference with Mr.</hi> D'assegny <hi>(another Minister there at that time;) And before that business was entred upon, Mr.</hi> De Laune <hi>prayed that Assembly, that his business might have been examined, and debated in the Assembly of both Colloquies, of the French and Dutch Churches.</hi> Whereto, (as in Article 18.) the Advise of the Colloquie was, <hi>that the business concerned directly, and particularly the French Churches,: And them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves would take cognisance (of the matter.)</hi> To which Articles we referr our selves, and desire (as being most remarkable,) that it may be observed, that the French Colloquie did determine that difference themselves; Notwithstanding that at the very same
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:38165:68"/> time, that Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> made his request as aforesaid, the Dutch Colloquie was then sitting in <hi>London:</hi> And afterwards a Synod did ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mble; But Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to appeal to them. Nor did the Dutch pretend any power, or jurisdiction in that busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or any other, wherein the French were solely interessed.</p>
            <p>And we doe find by our Book of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, that there have been not above sixe Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods in almost 80. years: whose assembling was, for the consulting, and advising toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in affairs of a generall nature, which publikely concerned both Nations, <hi>viz.</hi> As to petition the King, or Parliament, or Privie Councill, upon some matters, or other uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally concerning all Strangers in generall under their protection; or for to settle, and secure their Discipline severally, according to the forme thereof, when it was opposed by the Bishops, or otherwise drawn into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. At which times of their meetings; It is very observable, that the severall Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies of either Churches did sit distinctly, and apart by themselves to act, debate, determine and regulate all matters, and differences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Members of each Nation; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did so sit in Synod, at the same time for generall concernments, as aforesaid.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:38165:68"/>
            <p>Now before we can conclude this Treatise, We conceive it necessary, (for avoiding of all disputes, and removing all probable Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pules, that may perhapps be made, or arise,) to answer two main Objections, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be objected, <hi>Why will not Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>and the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families <hi>submit their differences to a</hi> Synod, <hi>composed of the Deputies of all the Churches, both</hi> Dutch <hi>and</hi> French <hi>in</hi> England; <hi>Being they are both incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated by one Patent, and thereby under one Ecclesiasticall government?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In answer whereto for the Readers satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, We admit it to be true, that we are both under one Patent; yet nevertheless that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent leaveth each Nation to its proper, and peculiar Ecclesiasticall Discipline, as before is specified; And for almost eighty years we have exercised a severall, and distinct Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for Church Government: And albeit the French have ever agreed with the Dutch in the main Essentials; yet they have alwaies differed in some Circumstantials: As for Example: The Dutch Churches have alwaies observed Holy daies: And for many years the French have not. The Dutch Ministers preach uncovered: And the French covered.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:38165:69"/> The Dutch Churches administer the Lords Supper the last Lords day, at the end of every two Moneths; and the French Churches the first Lords day in every Moneth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is evident, the exercise of our Discipline is various, and apart, and the power of either Churches independent one of another, as the Dutch have confessed.</p>
            <p>Again, (as the state of Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s, and our Affairs consists,) we cannot rationally be conceived to be so stupid, and obtuse, as to submit our differences to the decision of the Dutch Churches, conjoined with our own in Synod; Since that the Dutch Consistory in <hi>London</hi> have made themselves considerable parties therein, and been instrumental to effect (if they could,) that our differences might be determined by a <hi>Coetus;</hi> wherein they would chiefly predominate. And moreover, It is a usage amongst them, that when a Colloquie of the Dutch Churches assembleth in <hi>London</hi> (as of late years for the most part they doe;) Some Elders of that Church in <hi>London</hi> do serve, as Deputies for other absent Churches: Whereby there would be a greater number of Dutch Elders of the Church in <hi>London,</hi> (who are partially concerned, and interessed as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid,) than can be thought just, or equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in reason, or good Conscience.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:38165:69"/>
            <p>Lastly, the Dutch Elders have confessed, as before in our Letter to their Consistory is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, that they have no power, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of parties: Wherefore to consent to them is but to undo, and unravel, what hath been by ful assent of al parties condescended to already in referring all differences to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and the <hi>English Divines,</hi> as aforesaid; &amp; so thereby 2 whole years transactions for the peace, and quiet of our Churches should be rendred fruitless, and ineffectuall; And his <hi>Highness</hi>'s great care, and the pains of those <hi>Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> be totally made null, and inefficacious. But as things now stand, a Colloquie of the French Churches cannot be properly consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, so as to be conjoined with the <hi>Dutch;</hi> for that (besides they having been heretofore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted by the <hi>French Consistory</hi> in <hi>London,</hi>) many of them that are now capable to sit in Colloquie, are incompetent, being engaged on one side or other, and others are not capable, being either not rightly qualified, or else have acted so contrary to the Discipline of our Churches, that they ought not to be admitted. 2. It may be objected, <hi>Why have Mr.</hi> Delmey, <hi>and the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families, <hi>applyed to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, for help, and Relief: When as no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate hath any power to intermeddle in Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Censures? which is the matter, now in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion between them, and their Consistory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:38165:70"/>
            <p>To answer the same, We say; That We suppose the Reader will not expect from us, that we should definitively conclude, what the Magistrate's power is one way, or other; As is objected: In respect of our own private Capacities, and the difficulty of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For as much as we well know, that some do concede to the Magistrate too much Authority, and power to interpose in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall affairs; and others grant him too little; And there be some, that will allow him none at all. However we well know, that by many Examples in the <hi>Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> the Princes, and Rulers in <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> did for the Reformation, and good Government of the Church, extend their power to Ecclesiasticall matters; As did <hi>Asa, Hezekiah, Josiah, Nehemiah,</hi> and others</p>
            <p>But as to the matter of Fact, touching our Application to his <hi>Highness,</hi> on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and our selves. We hope it cannot be denyed; That as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime is, <hi>Whosoever hath power to give hath also to dispose, as he pleaseth:</hi> And as our Ancestours, being but Strangers in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could not erect at first our Church, without the grant and Licence of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt: So then it is but of naturall consequence
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:38165:70"/> to be admitted, That the King, and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors should have the common Patronage, and Protection of what was by them granted; When ever their aid, &amp; assistance was prayed in an extrordinary Case. Which hath happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us; In asmuch, as that before we ever petitioned his <hi>Highness;</hi> we had tryed all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinary waies and means whatsoever with the Consistory, as by this Treatise is obvious to all men. And the Reverend En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Divines, have reported to his <hi>Highness,</hi> that they conceive, that as well by the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt, as by several Acts of our Colloquies, his <hi>Highness</hi> is intituled to the cognisance of the business; For by that Patent, no Minister could be inducted into the Strangers Churches in <hi>London,</hi> unless he was first approved of by that King, or his Successours.</p>
            <p>And the Fathers of Families, petitioned his <hi>Highness</hi> in behalf of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and themselves, as being all of them obstructed, and hindred from enjoying their just Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and advantages, according to their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scipline and Government, granted them by the Liberty of that Patent; to wit, Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> being defeated of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Pastor lawfully chosen, and of his st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>end, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in recompence of his Charge: and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:38165:71"/> the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> being suspended from the Lords Supper, for no other Cause, but for defending Mr. <hi>Delmey</hi>'s innocence, and petitioning for Justice, and their rights to his <hi>Highness:</hi> Both which were deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them by their Consistory.</p>
            <p>And we have done no more in Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his <hi>Highness,</hi> than the Consistory themselves have done; onely We differ in the Manner: For We pray his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> to grant us in effect, an establishment of our Antient Governement by Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies: And the Consistory have proposed to, and prayed him, that a new Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticall form of Government might be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perinduced, and set up by a <hi>Coetus,</hi> or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. So that both of us by our own Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions have admitted power in his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> to settle us in peace, and confirm that Discipline, which of right doth belong to the <hi>French Churches</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> And how can it be otherwise done, but by his <hi>Highness</hi>'s examination, and interposition in those Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticall matters now in question, whereby to find out and discover, who hath, or who hath not transgressed; and thereby to understand the difference, and to give relief to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed according to justice.</p>
            <p>But to clear the objection fully, We shall
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:38165:71"/> positively assert, that his <hi>Highness,</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the premisses,) is rightfully intituled to the determination and Judgement of our Case; For as much as all parties have abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely consented thereunto; Which if the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> have the confidence to deny, We shall prove, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> 6. Elders, and 4. Deacons, (representing the whole Consistory,) submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before his <hi>Highness,</hi> (As before is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned,) That all differences should be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Colloquie of the Deputies of all the Churches, called by his <hi>Highness</hi>'s, Order; And in case they could not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them, then that ten, or twelve Godly <hi>Divines,</hi> (as his <hi>Highness</hi> should appoint,) should hear and decide the same, (if they could;) And if they could not, that his <hi>Highness</hi> should finally and conclusively settle, and adjudge the same: As by his <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi>'s last Order of Reference to the Divines (afore recited,) may appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This may be plainly manifested, in that the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> elected, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered their Deputies to attend that inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Colloquie, called by his <hi>Highness</hi>'s order, aswell as the other Churches.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After that Assembly could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly constitute, the said Consistory
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:38165:72"/> submitted to the English Divines, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them with seven several writings and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Thereby making their Defence to all the matters in question, as the said Divines have reported.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The said five persons, (taking upon them so irregularly the pretended form, and power of a Colloquie,) did by the Instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Consistory of <hi>London</hi> themselves, Censure them for their Submission before his <hi>Highness,</hi> to the hearing and decision of the <hi>English Divines.</hi> As by the translated Copy of their formall Act, taken in <hi>French</hi> by Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> 27. <hi>August,</hi> 1656. (Being then made,) and read by him unto them in presence of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Families</hi> may appear, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Company having considered the acquiescence of both parties, aswell of the</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory, <hi>as of the</hi> Fathers <hi>of</hi> Families <hi>to the Proposition of his</hi> Highness, <hi>touching the ten or twelve English Ministers, have condemned the one, and the other; It being greatly preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the authority of our Colloquies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This formall Act is very worthy of due Consideration; Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> and his Elders, (b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing present at, and causeing the making thereof against themselves, and the <hi>Fathers</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:38165:72"/> of <hi>Families,</hi>) without the knowledge at first of Mr. <hi>Delmey,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers of Families;</hi> As the said five persons can sufficiently justifie.</p>
            <p>And now whither We have not amply, and satisfactorily answered, and confuted the said Objections, by reason, proof, and positive Demonstration, We submit to the Reader's acceptance, and approbation. And if never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, the said Consistory shall alledge, that at length they protested in writing against their former submission to the English Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; We acknowledge, that we have heard so much, and that the Reverend Divines have certified the same to his <hi>Highness;</hi> But We affirme, That the Consistory did it, after they had presented their Papers of Defence to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and three Moneths after their first submission before his <hi>Highness</hi> at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> before specified. So that we conceive, they cannot be rationally excused by that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: For that, as their Protest was made too late; So was it also vain, and ridiculous, and ought so to be accounted and reputed; for as much as they have at severall times presented three, or four Petitions, touching the Differences in question to his <hi>Highness,</hi> and his <hi>Councill;</hi> Thereby admitting their power to give redress, and settle the same. All which we intreat the <hi>Courteous Reader</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:38165:73"/> specially to take notice of, and well to weigh and consider our aforesaid Answers to the said Objections; for that the Pamphlettors have in their Appendix, (in the very conclusion thereof,) professed; <hi>That they cannot consent, that Mr</hi> Delmey <hi>should be judged by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Ministers; as having never been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed in our Churches, and being wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the privileges, which they have enjoyed since their Establishment here.</hi> Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and assertion of theirs we request the Reader signally to remark, whither the same be to be credited; Their Submission being so plainly proved, and when as the same hath been done both by English, and Scotch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, as before is mentioned: And whither their disingenuity doth not aswell appear, in this very last Clause of their <hi>Appendix;</hi> as it doth also in the very first page of their Pamphlet; <hi>wherein they so covertly, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurely mention; that the French Church in</hi> London <hi>hath been troubled almost two years by Mr.</hi> Delmey; which we have so clearly, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently refuted. And being in all their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet they have only suggested, but not proved any one allegation; but on the contrary asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that, which the Dutch Consistory have denyed, as we have before fully proved; It <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>efore upon the whole matter submitted
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:38165:73"/> to the Judgement of the Reader, whither their <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>amphlet deserves to be credited, or any part <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ereof, being so clearly refuted and disproved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the body and parts of this our Treatise.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole Enarration, and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on of which Corollary, and Additions, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e entreat the Courteous Reader finally <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o judge betwixt Mr. <hi>Cisner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>heir party of the <hi>London</hi> Consistory, and Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elmey,</hi> and Our selves (the Fathers of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ilies, and other Members of the French-Church in <hi>London;</hi>) Whither (they having <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ade such a violent, and precipitate Irru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tion upon our Discipline and Government, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd still persist to evert, and dissolve it, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aving fomented others so to do in another Church,) they have not professedly, and of set-purpose oppressed, and injured Mr. <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> and our selves, as also that <hi>Walloon</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> And in that respect we hope, (notwithstanding that the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Consistories decline to give us satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,) That We shall be further vindicated, and absolved from their Imputations, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniations against us; And our Innocence, and Integritie be justified, and defended by the Reader's candid and benevolent Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; To which We have most unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and with much grief, and reluctance
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:38165:74"/> been necessitated to flie, and retire; As i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> our Epistle We have alledged. And were i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not to confine our selves to as much brevity as the necessary Circumstances of the matte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> require, We could haue super-added a mor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> prolixe Relation of our Grievances; Whic<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that the Reader might not be wearied, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> defatigate, We have omitted. And for tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Interruption, and Diversion, We have hereb<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> occasioned to his Christian patience, VV<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> most earnestly entreat him, (out of hi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Christian Compassion, and Sympathie to and with Us in our sad Distractions,) chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to remitt, and preterlapse.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38165:74"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>